He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels.
demons and saints. In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular
materialism, to see and to know reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality
like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
Post this live Colin show, focused on Enchantment in Creation.
The Union of the Scene.
and unseen as made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
The show was impressive in scope but easier to marvel at than to immerse yourself in. The staging
was static and pacing strange, the long, impressionist streaks in the first half, clumsily offset by
the frantically plot heavy ending, the musical portions as in all of West's religious projects,
were competent and occasionally ex...
excellent. He uses music from his own catalog judiciously, bringing Say You Will and its orchestral
code in and out as a recurring motif and finally fixing wolves. And that was from Rolling Stone's
review of Kanye West's 2019 musical opera, Nebuchadnezzar, which I have to thank you for letting
me even know that that exists. I just I'm I wish that that was our leading.
instead of the other guy.
Yeah, should we fire the voice of Steve who they're putting out there just to
spite me. Like they're putting him on that guy. The guy that was just to spite me.
No matter how much I complain or how it's shade I throw they just keep doing it.
I know. They did it last time too, is that recall? That's what I'm saying.
Yeah. There's a pattern here. Yep. Yep.
The pattern of a new sage should fade. I won't put up with this forever.
Well, since you say that, I'm Father, I just even day make and you are Father, Steven,
the young.
I'm sure you know that.
I'm sure your wife tells you that most days.
I can't believe you're beginning.
I can't believe you're reminded.
We're beginning our sixth year of the Lord of Spirit's podcast.
And what a lot of people may not know is that there was a secret pact made between you
and me.
Is this not so?
A secret pact.
Which you'll be in love.
now is being revealed.
first contact day, which is that you, you, you, you promised to do five years, at least,
of the Lord of Spirits podcast. So that means from now on since last time was our fifth
anniversary episode, we're all on borrowed time. So you're on borrowed time. All you favorite
giant killers and dragon slayers. The show could end next week at the conference.
It could happen right next week.
We are live though.
and starting in the second half of the show,
you can call us at 855-237-2346.
And if you make it past the great gatekeeper,
Mike Meradok-Baladin, again,
with your as he has requested on topic question.
And that's your cue to not be anywhere near the topic.
We might even talk back.
But first, a word from our sponsor.
So this episode of The Laura Spirits Podcast
is sponsored by the upcoming feature film,
Oh, ton-
Port Cristo, a Texas coastline, a brotherhood of monks,
inching their way towards St.
Hood.
El Tanto Pro Cristo is the first Orthodox,
full-length feature film made in America,
a cinematic pilgrimage with one night only events and
theaters across the country.
The national roadshow begins on October 6th in Dallas,
Texas, at the historic Texas theater.
From there, the film travels city by city one night at a time.
Executive producer Jonathan Peugeot calls it
Dangerous in the best way. I feel like a-
should read that like with a half French accent.
Deaserous, maybe.
Gessuid dangerous.
David Lauer.
He best.
It looks like Tarkovsky by way of Texas.
And for Dreech and Matthews Greenian calls it phenomenal.
Truly a work of art.
From award winning filmmaker Josh David Jordan and Emmy
not him in a composer, Michael Paraskevas.
This tour is underway with new dates being added.
So for tickets and showtimes, visit LTontoPoorCristos.com.
And if you'd like to bring the film to your own...
city, you can click the host tab to learn more. That's el tanto por Cristo.com. You should
you should probably spell that because a lot of these gringos don't know that there's
not an H in Cristo. It's true. E L T O N T O P O R C R I S T O dot com. I always want to
say dot com like whenever I'm seeing in the voice of Homestar Runner. Yes. Elton
Topore Cresto. That's Oh, no, god.
So yes, so so here we are out in the no man's
and the five year mark.
Yeah, you and I were two of a kind.
Oh, man, I haven't thought about that show forever.
We're going to find our way.
Wow.
Suddenly a tack of nostalgia there.
The great shoulder.
I know.
silver spoons man that was
Was that early 80s early 80s?
We were talking about the earlier today also early 80s show, but like the the main like living area.
In the house on silver spoons,
mm hmm, like no lie, pretty much looks like my living room today.
Really?
Yes, stand up arcade.
The whole thing.
Yeah.
Wow.
It wasn't deliberate.
Just worked out that way.
I was gonna say on their part as time travelers or
your part having this total nostalgia, blood.
Turns out my dream living room is the dream living room of a 10 year old in 1985.
Go figure.
A 10 year old multi-millionaire in 1980.
Well, things are cheaper now.
Coulding stand up arcade machine.
Yes.
Yes, much cheaper.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Well, so we're talking, we're heading back to ancient Babylon, which I know this is always
Big with the fans, the fans love it when we...
you stuff that's at least 3,000 years old or at least 2,500 years old.
I was going to say a lot of this stuff isn't 3,000 years old.
Yeah, yeah, not even quite.
But some of it is as you'll discover.
Yes.
Well, we always have to start a ways back from where we're actually talking about.
Indeed.
We keep rewinding.
I feel like that's a lyrical as well.
You've got to trace things.
Be kind, rewind.
So it feels what that means anymore.
So how about the old
Babylon like OG Babylon. What was that all about? What's up with that? Yeah. What's up with that?
Like you're you're doing a side-filled thing. What's the deal?
It was coming up in pre show. It's coming up with pre show with Mike and Simon.
Yeah. You know, so if that's a show about nothing, this is a show about everything.
Why do you keep pushing the elevator bun?
It doesn't make it come faster, guys. That's true.
So what makes Seinfeld's comedy so culturally important is the deep resonances,
not just the surface laughter but the acute social commentary.
Anyway, uh, yes, the city of Babylon.
So as you might have gleaned.
or might not from our references to Kanye West musical.
And we also could have made a bunch of matrix ship references.
Or Veggie Tales.
You know, Veggie Tales is just referring to the Bible.
That's true, but at least there's a whole Veggie Tale episode
about Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuchadnezzar.
Rack Shack and Benny.
Okay.
Very former so not me. Ben you tell us to little too young for me. Yeah, I'm gonna say I don't know, you know
But very formative for our elder millennial audience, you know, or our organ trail generation audience
Yeah, I think I think this a bit as died of dysentery, but anyway
So the city of Babylon is actually begins way before any kind of Babylonian Empire
Let alone the
the idea of Babylonian empire, which is where Nebuchadnezzar is located, but as is our
want, we're going to start all the way back there. The first things we know about Babylon
is a city really moving from the settlement stage to the city stage is back to be third
millennium BC, so think the mid 2000's BC, like 25, 2600 BC.
And so Babylon in a lot of ways, when you think about it, pre-rele the original Babylonian empire,
it's sort of like Byzantium in the sense that Byzantium was not a very significant city,
until St. Constantine came along and made it Constantinople, and then all of a sudden it became a very, very significant city.
The same is kind of true of Babylon.
So it was a relatively
insignificant city in a cod. We've talked about this in various episodes before on the show that Mesopotamia
was divided into two sections, a generally southern section, Sumer, and then a northern section, a cod, and that
even though in some ways these two sides are culturally close, like you can talk about Mesopotamian culture in general.
That's all.
and there are certainly lots of features
that apply to both.
You also have a great distinction culturally,
specifically as it regards language.
Yeah, I mean, Sumerian and Akkadian
are not remotely related.
Like they are not,
you know, it's not like Hebrew and Arabic
which right next to each other, both Semitic languages.
Sumerian and Akkadian are not,
I think isn't Sumerian a language isolate
and Akkadian is a Semitic language?
Mary does not relate to anything.
Yeah, it's just its own thing and then a cadian is sort of the ure level
Pun intended
Semitic language from which other Semitic languages are ultimately derived sort of in the same way that Sanskrit is for Indo-European languages
so
Yeah, the only way those two languages are related is that
because Sumerian is older, there are some loan words.
There are some Sumerian words that sort of find their way
into a Cadian, or that continue to be used by a Cadian speakers.
There's not a separate Cadian word for whatever that is.
They just use the Sumerian word.
But those are actually relatively rare.
Almost everything in ancient Mesopotamia had
an Acadian Semitic Word or N-
or title and then assume Aryan equivalent. So the end within the history of Mesopotamia,
the influence of various cities in the region would rise and fall and sometimes a city or group
of cities in Sumer would become kind of dominant, sometimes a city or cities in...
a cod would become dominant.
And they'd sort of go back and forth.
So we talked about, for example, when we talked about Abraham in that episode, we talked
about how Abraham was born in Ura during what's called the Ura 3 period, even though there
was no Ura 2 period.
That was a period where the city of Ura in particular, and its culture, as part of the Sumerian
Renaissance came to prominence and zoom.
sort of that region became sort of dominant over a cod. A few centuries later, you get to
that we'll talk about more here in a minute, the original Babylonian Empire, which was centered
around Babylon, which is in a cod. So that's one such shift that happened. And when we're
We're talking about the third millennium BC when we're talking about before...
the Babylonian Empire proper in the Second Millennium BC.
When we talk about the dominance of Mesopotamian culture or influence,
or war and Sumerian culture or a Cod and Acadian Subitite culture,
we're not talking about an empire like you would have later.
Yeah, it's sort of a significant city state with kind of dependent countryside nearby.
Run.
And certain cultural things, right?
So obviously, you know, the Sumerians invent writing.
They invent kuneiform writing.
Well, that takes off, right?
Everyone adopts that.
So think of, if you want a contemporary equivalent,
think of the way American culture, American movies,
and pop culture stuff sort of shows up everywhere, right?
Even in places where the US military isn't bombing or occupying.
Um.
few of those two. But even to the ones where we're not at all, there's still these American
cultural things. So that's what we're talking about, that's what I mean, influence. In
the third millennium BC, until you get to, that's sort of the genius of the original Babylonian
empire, is they kind of invent the idea of an empire. They're kind of the first ones
to work out the logistics of being able to control a vast swath of territory. Because
Do you have to remember what's going on?
on with travel at this point in history on foot, right? And this sort of thing, just administering
anything that large effectively was previously sort of considered impossible, until the
Babylonians sort of figured that out and cracked that nut. And then of course the other major
world power during that period was Egypt.
Which...
was already ancient by the time that the Babylonian Empire starts. The Second millennium BC,
an Egyptian culture similarly had great influence, especially around the Mediterranean basin.
The Mesopotamian influence was more within the fertile crescent, what we would call the fertile crescent.
So that changes.
when at the beginning of the Second Millennium BC, the Amuru, who we've talked about before,
which means Westerner who are super people living in Syria also known as the Amurites.
The original Old West. Yes. Notice the Amurites in the Bible.
come and move east and invade and settle in and make back.
Babylon, the city of Babylon, their heartland and their capital.
And these folks have a knack for military strategy, for trade strategy, for logistics, and build the Babylonian empire.
And of course, as we mentioned many times on the show, the most famous, the most famous one of these, Amuru, is Hamarabi.
The food game in terms of promise
and sort of the old Babylonian empire of the Second millennium BC at its peak under
Hammarabi. People know about his law code, but there's far more than that. He sets up literally
consolidates a sort of world culture. He establishes the logistics for a world cultural exchange,
world trade for being able to move.
military units in a way that wasn't possible before.
He, uh, and of course, this is called the Bronze Age because they master the smelting of bronze.
And when we talk about the Babylonian Empire smelting bronze, as we mentioned on the show before,
they're getting the copper from Cyprus. That's where Cyprus gets its name. And they're getting the tin
from what's now Afghanistan.
Yeah, so this exchange, you know, these trade networks that bring these two substances together
Essentially are the basis for a lot of the technology of the time
It's like you know, they're kind of like rare earth metals are for us today in some ways right now
Yeah, and so but that shows you the span from Cypress to have get us that they were able to
Utilize resources, you know natural resources that are that diverse in that far apart
Yeah, right effectively.
How Marabi really liked the style of leather sandals that they wore in Crete so he would get them imported to where?
imported Crete and sandals
So but this shows you how just how interconnected the world was
Under the Babylonians we tend to think that you know
We talk about our modern technology. Oh, it's made the world so much smaller
You know now we can go right but with Bronze Age technology the Babylonians effectively did that with the known world at the time
And of course, then as we get toward the end of the second Leninian BC, it all comes crashing down.
You get the Bronze Age collapse. And the Bronze Age collapse is a product of a whole bunch of
things. Most folks agree now that one of the core elements of it was climate change.
Yeah, cause people...
Even though they didn't have cars.
Even though they didn't have cars, it's true.
Yeah, because like, you know, areas that formerly were fertile
were no longer fertile.
And so the populations were living off of those now infertile areas
moved, and they often moved to where there were other people.
Right. And so that caused, you know, people watching survive.
And so they start fighting for resources. Yes.
Yeah, exactly.
You guys have asked migrations.
and talk before about the C-People's Invasion,
that this-
figures into Egypt. And so all of this infrastructure, all of these
empires, all of these major powers collapse. And it's not instant, but it's
relatively quick. It's over the course of like a century. The things really
come crashing down.
That we've used bronzes in example, but it's a good example for this too, right?
Once all of those trade routes and everything are broken and all of that logistical network
is destroyed, right?
It becomes basically impossible to make bronze because you can't bring together the copper
and the tin from the other ends of either end of the world.
And so during that period, I think we've mentioned this on the showbuff.
And you see this reflected in the Bible in the early Iron Age, they viewed things made of
bronze as if they were like magic.
Yeah.
Like quite literally.
That's part of the subtext when David meets Goliath and they describe Goliath's armor
and weapons and they're all made of bronze.
Yeah.
Right.
Like, no one was able to even make bronze anymore.
We found like in Philistine temples, we found like really dumb
things made out of bronze, like chariot hitches and stuff, that are just like pegs, just bronze
metal pegs, found them in the most holy part of the temple as an artifact. Because that stuff
all just becomes impossible. It's not called the Iron Age because Iron was an improvement in
technology. Iron is not an improvement over bronze really. It's much more brittle. When you get
get to steal you're doing okay but just iron itself it rusts you know.
corrodes very easily. And so the early Iron Age there is no real world empire. Egypt survives,
but it survives basically because it repels like the sea peoples who settle on their border.
So Egypt is kind of hemmed in. They're not able to exert power and control beyond Egypt.
And so the world of like Saul and David, as we've said before, is sort of a post-apocalyptic world.
the dissents, right? They're living in the ruins of a civilization that is collapsed.
Um, it's that includes the Babylonian Empire and Babylon is still a city, right? It's still
there, but declines in prominence steeply, um, elements of the city, like literal buildings
and things start to fall into disrepair, right? It just babble on...
as always in general decline.
So the next real empire that shows up on the scene
is the Assyrians.
I feel like whenever we mention the Assyrians,
we should have some kind of boo track, you know.
Woo.
Some of the Church of the East people might, you know,
miss here.
Wow, okay.
But ancient Assy.
ha ha
i i don't know why they would
They've named themselves after the Assyrians.
I don't know.
I've been spending a lot of time in Jonah lately.
So of course, you know, that's big on the radar there.
Yeah.
So the Assyrians in a couple of ways are kind of like the Romans later.
And here are the couple of ways they resemble the Romans.
Number one, brutality.
So for the Romans, you could think about them,
I'm sultately earthy carthage
You could think of them, you know, crucifying people and mass to make a point.
Using crucifixion in general to make a point, right?
Just brutality and cruelty is a tactic.
When you read conquest accounts from the Assyrians, they'll talk about like after they, you know,
destroy the city, they'd stack all of the men's heads in one pile and the women's heads
in another pile and the children's heads in another pile.
and then measure how tall the piles were and report that information.
For my favorite is when their king decided to take the heads off of a number of his nobles
and made those heads into a necklace and wore it around.
Yeah, yeah.
They would skin people alive and hang the skin publicly for the next city to see.
So these are the kind of people we're talking about.
like the
They make pull pot look like Mr. Rogers, right?
Like these are truly brutal folks.
The other way in which they're kind of like the Romans
is that the Romans kind of appropriated Greek culture.
Right?
Like there are distinct, you look at like the Etruscans
There are distinct, like, cultural elements.
and stuff there. But it kind of gets overpowered by a lot of Greek cultural elements in, and
there's sort of an inferiority complex that I think the, the, the Romans and the Greeks,
it's I think is sort of like Americans and British people, like where we think anybody
with a British accent is smart. Yes, it's a prestige thing. You know, there's just sort
of this general like, you know, and I.
sort of the same thing with the Romans and the Greeks, right? The Greeks just seemed really smart.
The Romans, so they got a complex and so they, you know,
right, bad sequels to their stuff like Virgil did.
Here we go. You know, what I love about you making that reference to the in need is that it always
gets our friend, the living Rick Roll, you know, gets his hackles up. Yeah. Yeah, I mean,
Isn't it the case that Romans, I mean, we're kind of getting off check a little bit here, but did
Romans and a number of times kind of complain like, hey, we conquered those Greeks.
And yet why is it that all the kids are into Greek literature?
Right.
Yeah.
Like culturally they were conquered.
Right.
So the same is the same is kind of true with the Assyrians.
That's why we're bringing this up with the Romans and the Greeks.
The Assyrians kind of co-opt Mesopotamian culture.
Yeah.
So none of uh is another city that was basically nothing.
before the rise of the Assyrian Empire and then making it its capital. It's not even where
they're from. Yeah, they're called Asur. Yeah. Asur. Yeah. Um, so us are named after their
main god, ashur. Yes. Yes. Yeah. And so that's why they're called Assyrians, but they make
it, set up Nineveh as a capital. It's not even where they're from. I mean, Nineveh is in
area but it's a different city and was sort of nothing until they until they
establish it. But so these are not cities that were prominent at some point in the past
in sumer, they're not in sumer, but in a cod even, right? But they sort of take over all of
the previous Mesopotamian traditions and literature, sometimes literally. So we have a lot of the
text we have that are old Babylonian texts, meaning from the original Babylonian Empire.
the Second millennium BC, we have a lot of significant texts where the texts that we have,
at least cataloged, aren't the original old Babylonian versions. They're the Assyrian versions
from the libraries at Nineveh. So at Nineveh, they not only collected all of these texts,
but they translated them into the Assyrian dialect of Akkadian. At this point in history,
So
So in at the beginning of the first millennium BC, you start to get language families diverging
in the Near East.
So you get like Hebrew and Ugritic and some of these other languages emerging from Old
Canaanite around 1000 BC and separating.
That's why when you read like Joshua and Judges and even the first bit, so first Samuel,
Everybody can understand each other.
Yeah, it's like are they speaking different languages? It's like, well, sort of right now
they're all speaking dialects of old cana knight, right? So there's a lot of overlap,
right? And the same thing is happening in Mesopotamia with a cadian. You start getting
in a Syrian dialect of a cadian. You're going to get a neo-Babalone and dialect of a cadian.
They're still basically a canyon, but you can tell.
Right, that there are certain ways of writing certain words, certain verb forms and stuff
that market out is being the Assyrian dialect in particular.
So they not only collect all that literature to have a library at Nivea, but they put their
tweaks and twists on all of it, right, to sort of make it their own.
And so also the Assyrians...
tried to establish a monoculture.
Yeah, a serialization or so.
Yeah, a notification.
And we've talked about that before,
on the show in terms of what happens to the Northern Kingdom of Israel, the Northern tribes.
How when a Syria conquers them, they deport all the people from that land,
from Samaria, take them over and put them somewhere else in Mesopotamia.
and they take people from us at Potemia and
relocate them to that land in the Levant. Right. And then over a couple generations,
the Hebrew names disappear. Right. Like they just get merged into the general Assyrian,
Mesopotamian population. And so this was deliberate on their part. This was part of how they
manage their empire to try to prevent revolts is...
by homogenizing everybody's culture.
So you're living and working on land
that your family doesn't have any real connection to
for any long period of time.
You are not culturally different
in what we would today in modern terms called
ethnic group from your neighbor,
whose family has been there for generations, right?
And all become sort of this melting pot idea, right?
And that worked okay for them for a while.
But the Assyrians were mostly concerned, and this is why they used that strategy.
Their concern was that they were going to have revolts out at the edges of the empire in
newly conquered territory.
Because we've got to remember at this point in history, you can only fight wars during
a certain season, so there are no standing armies.
No such thing as a standing army.
There are generals who a king has whose job is to muster and move and command troops.
But the troops are just regular men of a certain age range who you call up, right?
These are not professionals.
And most of them are farmers.
Because this is a subsistence period in history.
Most people are just working on making food and it's...
everyone's if most people are not doing that, you die. You don't have food to eat. Yeah. So if you
you can't just go and deploy your army for three years straight because that means no one's growing any
crops. So now can you not feed that army? You can't feed any of your people at home. Right. So
this I know this seems weird from a modern perspective, but literally after the harvest was done,
I'm done.
Right?
At a certain point.
Oh, now...
the time for war, we call everybody up, we march them somewhere, we make war, right?
And then at a certain point, we've got to march them all back for the planting seasons.
So yeah, it's time out, right?
We'll be back.
And then everybody goes back to their respective corners, grows their food for the year.
And then after the harvest again, game on and everybody comes back and attack.
It's just the reality.
Okay, and so,
And the area goes and brutally captures some piece of territory, right?
As soon as they march back, march out of there, what's to stop them from breaking away?
Right? Well, they've relocated all the people, right?
They took all the people from there back with them.
Right? And then the next season, they send the military out with the new settlers to help them settle. Right?
So they're concerned about the edges.
Okay.
What
they weren't thinking about was that the call might come from inside the house.
Yeah, so that they could have an internal uprising.
Yes, the things could happen inside.
Add spoilers.
This is what happens to the Assyrians.
Guess who's back?
It's Babylon.
Yeah.
Well, first, first, the first sign that maybe the Assyrian Empire isn't as strong as it
once was.
So...
We get into the early 620s BC.
The Assyrian Emperor is a fellow named Sincharis Kun,
which was trippingly off the tongue.
Another one not to name your kids.
Yes, no, this is definitely not a saint.
This is definitely not a saint.
Last night, the Bible study we talked about,
what I'm sure was a lovely young woman in the Torah,
but who was given the name by her father.
Hogla. Oh man. That wouldn't work well here. Yeah. I said, if you name your daughter Hogla,
I will not baptize them Hogla. Yeah. If I do someday they will kill you and I will not blame them.
But yeah, Sinchar's Kuhn is not even eligible for David your kid in the Orthodox Church.
So he's the emperor, and the first sign of his overall weakness comes with another...
fellow named Sinsumulisher. Also trippingly flows off the tongue. Yes. So don't get Sinshara
Skun and Sinsumulisher confused. These are two different guys. Okay. Sinsumulisher was
one of his generals. I mean I can't wait to see what the auto captioning does with those.
Oh, this is gonna be great. Yeah.
Uh, similar. Sure.
So since he was a Lissier is one of Sincharis Koon's generals and
He's one of the first ones to smell weakness around the emperor and
So he
Stages a revolt to try to take the throne leading to a minor and fairly short civil war because he has some partisans some military
Partisans on his side, but he kind of gets ended but just the fact that this happened
The fact that it's in charge.
to take the time to put down such rebellion is taken by a bunch of people as a sign of weakness.
Right. And the most important of those is a fellow by the name of Nabopalacir.
Another one, not to name your kids.
Yeah, and Nebopalacir, his name in Babylonian dialect of
of a Canadian means now...
Naboo protect this sun. Naboo being a God. One of the gods. Yeah. Naboo is the eldest son of
Marduk. We'll be talking about Marduk a lot in the second half. Not a bellon. And Naboo
Polasser kind of comes from nowhere, but there's an interesting theory about where he comes from
that we'll get to here in a couple of minutes. But in the one place where he mentions his heritage,
She says he is a son.
of a nobody. That's a weird, weird self designation. I mean, I'll miss everybody in the
ancient world, who's somebody who we're trying to be somebody claims to be like the son
of a god. Right. Yeah. Or at least just names their father. Right. Like, yeah. Even if he
wasn't significant, right. But he says he's a son of a nobody. We'll get to in a minute
The theory is to what that's pointing to.
And so, Nahuil Pulaszor, seeing Sincharis Kun as weak, decides now is the moment for what
begins with Nahuil Pulaszor as a sort of independence movement.
He wants Babylon and the cities around it, referred to as Babylonia, the region of Babylon,
So basically secede from the Assyrian Empire.
Let me become a separate unit.
But he's not, he doesn't directly attack Sinchariskoon.
Yeah, he doesn't try to make himself emperor at this point, right? He just wants to succeed.
And so he took control of the cities of Babylon, Uruk and Nippur.
Uruk, remember, is the city Gilgamesh is from.
Also, remember, Uruk is the Sumerian word for city.
Yeah.
We're going to see a lot of cities here with Ura elements.
Yes.
So you have Ura, just Ura, right?
Where Abraham's from.
But you also have Urook.
You have Nippur, Sippur, right?
And that's the city of and then the prefix, which
is often a god, a god's name, right?
The city of that god, right?
Babylon, setting the way back machine,
we actually talked about this.
Babylon's name actually is from Bob Ely.
Bob being the Akkadian word for gate, Ely being the plural gods. So it's a gate of the gods.
So he takes a role of Babylon, Uruk and Nippur. And after taking control of those cities and
signaling their intent to secede, he was crowned the king of Babylon.
As you might expect, the Sinsharskun
not cool with this. And so he counter-attacked and he managed to take Uruk back and he took
Nippur back briefly, leaving Nabbo-Palacir with just Babylon in its environs. But before we talk
about what happened next, brief pause about Nabbo-Palacir's potential origin story.
Yes, where is this guy from?
Where is he coming from? What is Santa...
nobody mean why is he doing this? Why is he after independence? Okay, so we have this tablet.
And the tablet is about is talking about an order issued by Sinchariskun,
regarding a fella named Kadooru.
Now, we're jumping ahead, but if you remember past times that we've talked about Nebuchadnezzar,
we're Nebuchadnezzar as popped his head up on the show, we've pointed out that as actual
name in Babylonian is Naboo Kaduru Utsur.
So Kaduru is like the middle part of that.
And is how it would commonly be abbreviated?
It's a nickname.
Right, so if you are going to a brief
We create someone's Babylonian name.
So, Nabbo Polasser, if there was someone who was friendly enough with him, maybe his wife
or something, it was going to call him like a nickname.
They wouldn't call him Nabbo or Nabby or something like we would.
They would call him Pola.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So, the same way, Nebuchadnezzar would be, you'd call him Kaduru, right?
So, it's possible that this person's name was actually Nebuchadnezzar.
Right.
but we don't know.
a decent speculation. Right, right. That's fairly, there's a fairly strong case for that. Okay. Yeah. But whoever this guy was, he
got on the outs.
Wishing Chariskun said some critical things, maybe made some critical moves. He was apparently part of and one of the ancient families of
of Uruk, so he's kind of a prominent citizen of Uruk who did these things, but then died
before.
Shara's Koon could do anything about it.
And so the tablets in Shara's Koon decides he can still do something about it.
So he being the Assyrian Emperor and being the kind of person who's the Assyrian Emperor
sent troops to dig up his body, this Kadoor's body,
and then have it dragged through the city until it disintegrated.
Yeah, which is basically how in this time place cultural content
text, you'd damn someone to hell.
Yes, you're kind of erasing them.
Yeah, yeah.
Okay.
The tablet mentions he has two sons.
The one son whose name is intact on the tablet has a name that begins with Naboo.
The second son's name also begins with Naboo, but...
the rest of the name is kind of cracked, broken out of the tablet. So we don't know if it
says Nabopalacir or not. But based on the time the tablet is from, based on connections
we've already talked about, and some more we'll talk about the future between Nabopalacir
and Uruk and his family in Uruk. There is a going theory and this whole son of
nobody thing is that Nabeopalacir was this Kadooru's son. And that this being done to his
father by Sinsharskun is what motivates him to then start this uprising. And if this
Kadooru's full name was Nebuchadnezzar, that would explain why Nabeopalacir is going
to name his son Nebuchadnezzar also. Yes. So after his now gone father, but he's
He's sent of a nobody.
because the Syrian Emperor has made him a nobody.
Yeah.
So it's a lot of conjecture,
but it happens to kind of fit the facts that we do have.
It explains all the data we have,
but we don't have any positive evidence to prove it's true.
Yeah.
It's just a good explanation for the evidence we have.
Right.
But so back to our tale of woe.
Ah so...
Navajo Polasser, he's down to just Babylon itself and it's immediate
environments. He's lost to a rock. He's lost Nippur back to
San Chariscoon. And then what happens is he's not again, the only one who
I smell weakness around the history and emperor, right? Because now we had
this civil war. He had to put down now he's losing cities to
have a polasser and so another
one of his officials, whose name we don't know because Sinchariskyun blotted it out,
trying to seize the throne while Sinchariskyun was trying to deal with the Abba Palacir.
I mean, these are the Assyrians.
Yes.
Right.
It only makes strike with the Iarzhat.
Exactly.
You are being captured of a Klingon ship.
This is how you do it.
Right.
So, um, so this attempted coup d'état happens back home.
and Sharerscune has to go back to Nine of-
to deal with that, right? So he has to withdraw his troops from Babylonia to deal with that.
And that then allows a noble palacer to take back Nippur. He doesn't get Uruk back,
but he gets Nippur back. Once in Charisquoon has to withdraw, that is referred to by Sin
charisquen after he puts it down. He blotted out the name.
So this is more of that making some.
nobody thinks. And Charles Cun glutted out the name of the guy who tried the coup. So he don't
know what his name was because he had all records of that person's existence destroyed after he put
down the coup. But he referred to that as the 100-day revolution, right, because he put it down
in less than 100 days, right. He had dealt with it. But this allowed Nabo Pulaszor to sort of consolidate
the time you get to 620 BC with
in Babylonia. He's sort of firmly in charge at this point. And watching Sincharis Kuhn
have to go and retreat and having to deal with these, he's running around having to put
out fires. This emboldens Nabo Pulaszor. Nabo Pulaszor decides, you know, let's make Babylonia
a little bigger.
Right. He's breathing room. And so he starts heading north. By the time you get to 616 BC,
unified pretty much all of
Mesopotamia under his rule. And the Assyrians are basically now confined to Syria in terms
of where they have power. Now the Assyrians at this time had made a peace deal with the
Egyptians. Yeah, I mean, mutual. Let's not hurt each other. We've got bigger fish to
fry. Yeah, treaty essentially a non-aggression pact. Yeah, right. Egypt need to deal with
trying to repel this.
The Syrians had enough stuff going on.
They didn't need to try and deploy the military.
They need to try to conquer Egypt.
That was just beyond what they could likely do.
And so they just sort of agreed to border areas.
And the Levant was sort of a demilitarized zone in a way
in that they both tried to project their influence over it,
but neither of them would go in and invade and try to conquer it.
Be on the...
northern kingdom being gone. So the Egyptians, part of this deal, right, was that was sort of
mutual, mutual defense. So if someone attacked Egypt, the Assyrians would come help. If someone
attacked the Assyrians, Egypt would come help. So Egypt sent troops to Syria to try to help
the Assyrians against Nabopalacers.
expansion and failed miserably. So Egypt's military force got significantly weakened through a
series of losses and they eventually abandoned for the most part the Assyrians. Now all of this
happening, right? So now Naba Palacir is shrinking and shrinking the Assyrian Empire. Who else gets
to wind and swells
weakness, but the meads. Oh, hey, the meads inventors of the
trapper keeper.
Everybody, everybody show your Gen X cards. Yeah. So the
meads kind of get rid of this and the meads, so the the
meads never really have their own empire. The meads, if you
want to think of the meads, you have to think of the meads
sort of like the Huns, right? I mean, under Attila, the Huns
or the other barbarian groups, the Vandals, who sacked Rome, right, they were sort of more
of a tribal group. They weren't into logistics and trade and rule and stuff. They were more
into sort of pillaging. And so the needs throughout the second half of the First Millennium
B.C. essentially operate on a mercenary basis for other empires. Right. And
And so the means they'll get win.
Hey, these Assyrians, they're a pretty big empire.
They got a lot of gold.
They got a lot of nice stuff.
And they're on the back foot.
They're weak right now.
And so the means start raiding and pillaging Assyrian cities,
sort of on their own at first, throughout 615 and 614 BC.
And that includes them moving into even us
or the Assyrian homeland.
And they're
pillaging cities. And so the Babylonians see them doing this and say, Hey guys, looks
like we're on the same side here. Right? So essentially, the Babylonians and the
Meads make a treaty. We'll talk about that more in a little bit here. But they make a treaty.
And so the Meads fight for the Babylonians. They get to be part of the Babylonian
military. As it's marching on the Assyrians, they get to keep what they pillage and loot
on the way, right?
So it's a win-win situation as far as the needs are concerned.
Right.
They've got a lot of backup.
They're getting stuff, right?
It's easier for them to raid and capture stuff
because they're with this other military force.
And so in 612, we see the needs and the Babylonian army
Lace each to Nineveh.
And they Lace.
siege to Nineveh, the capital of Syrians for several months, and end up pillaging and raising
the city. As part of that, according to ancient accounts, including Barosis, so we've talked
about recently, they break the river walls and flood the city. That's part of the breaking
the siege.
level of pillage the place.
St.
Charis Kuhn ends up dead.
We're not sure who exactly is the one who killed him or how he died, but he
ends up dead by the end of the destruction of Nineveh.
And Nineveh is just allowed to kind of rot.
It remains in ruins from that point.
With St.
Charis Kuhn dead, his son,
Asher Ubal at the second.
who is a total loser, technically becomes a Syrian emperor.
Yeah.
I say technically because like the capital just got destroyed.
They've lost all of their cities.
They've lost their heartland.
He's kind of the emperor of Jack and squat and Jack left town.
Right.
Yeah.
So he goes on the run.
Right.
because he knows the
He just technically inherited his death warrant as far as the Babylonians are concerned
As far as the devil palacias concerned so he goes on the run and basically goes and hides with the Egyptians
He takes what's left of the Assyrian military
they run south to
Egypt
And say hey remember you're supposed to defend us right?
And so probably not because the Egyptians cared at all about
about Asher Ubal at the second?
Right, or the Assyrians, but probably more because they had considered the Assyrians a major threat and that major threat just got wrecked, meaning the Babylonians are now an even more major threat potentially.
The Pharaoh Neco, the second, the inventor of the wafer,
Uh, goes out and uh,
for another second went out.
to war with the Babylonians and the big climactic battle, the big clash happens in 605 BC,
the Battle of Carcomish, which happens in and around the area of Maguito.
That's where they meet up, right?
Where the Babylonians coming in the one direction and the Egyptians coming up in the other direction,
where they run into each other.
long story short, the Egyptians get wrecked.
pretty much destroyed. And with the defeat of the Egyptians there and the retreat of the
Egyptians back to their borders, the Babylonian Empire is established. The Neobab... what's called
the Neobabalone Empire. The new Babylonian Empire is established in there in 605 BC. And right after
that battle and the official establishment of the Neobabalone Empire, which is ruled over by the
the Caldience the Cald-
Deans are an ethnic group. So Caldean technically refers to the primary ethnic group of the neo-Babolonian
empire. And they kind of become like the ruling house sort of, although a little bit broader than that.
Yeah. Now we remember we mentioned this back of the Abraham episode that referring to Er of the
Caldees was sort of a radical anachronism there. Yeah. Right. Because there weren't any Caldeans yet.
Calvian properly speak-
refers to the neo-Bavilonian empire. But that is one of those places in the Torah where we're getting like an update.
Right. Like, or, or where? Right? Oh, the one over in Mesopotamia. Right? So Caldia is how they would refer to that region later.
But so a few months after that the impairs established, battle of carcabish big victory and then
Navajo Pellacetize.
before the end of the year. So, Nava Polasser is in certain ways like Alexander the Great
in that he has this final victory of his conquest and then dies and never really rules over
the empire he established. But his son does. Nebuchadnezzar II, we finally got to him.
Yeah, this is the one that is sort of the Nebuchadnezzar of the Bible.
is the Dominican Ezra of the Bible.
He is the eldest son of
Nabopalacir. He is at the time of the death of Nabopalacir.
He is officially crowned as the king of Sumer and Akkad,
Owen also the king of the universe.
Nice.
I actually looked it up and the original Babylonian king
had the title of King of the Four Corners of...
No, Hammer Robby. Sorry. Yeah, Hammer Robby,
King of the Four Corners of the World.
Yeah, yeah, moving up now.
So, universe even is, yeah, leveling up.
It glutes the heavens.
You have the seas.
So, as we mentioned earlier,
Nabukuduru, Utsur is the actual original.
This has caused certain pedants
to want to say, never could dress her
instead of never could nether
when they're translating the Bible.
Which such people ought to be watched closely.
Yeah, yeah, so.
This name means Naboo watch over this sun or my air.
And there are apparently some people who say,
I don't know the truth of this,
but there are some people who say that Nebuchadnezzar
versus Nebuchadnezzar.
Nebuchadnezzar is some kind of Israelite joke
because it would maybe translate to Naboo protect the mule.
Yeah, depending on how you vowel it.
Yeah, which is I guess hilarious,
Ancient Near Eastern humor we're following him but
Mule, I mean, Mule, Mule's pretty, I mean, that's one of the most timeless kinds of joke references. Yeah, I mean, yeah, you know,
if an Arabic you call someone jahash or hamar. Yeah, you know, no, I'm cussing on the on the air and Arabic, but anyway,
just the animal names. They're just animals.
Yes, so this is true story of
Dutch life
When my dad was a little kid his grandmother my great grandmother used to refer to him all the time as Duma Fricka Azal
As one does and he thought it was some Dutch term of indierman or something he only found out
Later that it's Dutch for dumb fat donkey. Wow
Wow.
This is what Dutch family studio is, man.
This is, yeah.
I mean, there are no feelings.
So,
right.
Not left after that, you know, your old grandma, right?
It's right.
So,
so,
so, yeah, so he, as we mentioned, he's Nebuchadnezzar the second.
That is not based on the idea that he's, that Nabbo Polasser's father was named Nebuchadnezzar,
though that is very possible.
And that may have,
He was me while he was named that, because he was not King of Babylon.
Right.
He is Nebuchadnezzar II because he is the second Babylonian emperor to have that name,
the first one being one of the last emperors of the Old Babylonian Empire.
Nebuchadnezzar I was in the 12th century and the second half will talk about him a little more.
In the waning days, in the collapsing days of the Old Babylonian Empire, Nebuchadnezzar I tried to
sort of make Babylon great again and it didn't go so swell.
But so he's at the 12th century.
B.C. the very end in the middle of the Bronze Age collapse.
But that's the previous emperor Nebuchadnezzar, Babylonian emperor Nebuchadnezzar, which makes
him the second.
While he was crowned prince before Nebuchadnezzar died, Nebuchadnezzar, the second did a couple
of important things.
his official position was he was the high priest of air.
He may remember.
the god Aya from some of the flood stories we read last time.
Yep.
It was the most high god in a lot of those Mesopotamian stories, but he was the high priest of Aya in
Uruk.
So this is another connection between that family and the city of Uruk.
And this was fairly common.
People don't realize how long this lasted in the ancient world.
Like Julius Caesar's first significant position in Rome was a priesthood.
that Hagen priesthood was a government office.
Essentially.
So having the crown prince be a priest,
because remember that the king was also the high priest of the empire.
And these ancient empires.
So the crown prince having a priesthood was fairly common, a prominent priesthood.
He also, the other major thing he did is that Nabbo-
was not leading the army into battle at Carcomish,
Nebuchadnezzar was.
He as crown prince was the one actually on the ground
at Carcomish, at Meghito, leading his army into battle
against the Egyptians and winning that decisive battle.
So when he ascends to the throne,
it's not just a biological claim as Navajo-Pilassus' son.
He's also accomplished in his own right.
that as he comes in.
to take the throne. He was also, uh,
the Mokinesh's wife, he was married to the daughter of Syaraxes.
Syaraxes is not a mortal combat character.
Syaraxes was the king of the Meeds.
So when we mentioned a few minutes ago that
Nava Polaster made this deal with the Meeds
that's part of how they cemented that treaty. He married his first born son
to the dog.
of the King of the Meads to submit that alliance. So once one
Stabicad Ezra comes to the throne and becomes the self-styled King of the
universe, he he sets about consolidating the Empire because the Empire has just
been won right so there's a lot of things that need to now happen and the first
First of those.
that he sets about is firming up the borders.
So having won the Battle of Carcomish,
he's sort of cemented Babylonian influence
over the Levant and Syria,
but hasn't really conquered it, right?
Has it really assimilated into the neo-Babalonean empire?
He's just kind of, I mean, the Syrians are gone
the Egyptians have been pushed.
back out of it. And so his first order of business in terms of consolidating the Empire
is to send troops in, March troops down to consolidate, make that, all that territory
officially part of his empire. He first marches down the coast, down the Mediterranean
coast. So he takes what was Felicia and goes all the way down to the border with Egypt
in by 601 BC has some skirmishes with Egypt.
that basically end with establishing, okay, here's the border between the neo-Babalone and empire
and Egypt. They both push back and forth for a little bit and then kind of settle resolve.
And what this means is Judah, which at this point with the northern kingdom gone, is kind of a
postage stamp as we mentioned in a previous episode of a kingdom. It's tiny, it's not only tiny,
but it's also surrounded.
Yeah.
So the Babylonian Empire is...
between them in the coast, meaning shipping's not really happening, trying to ship overland.
They got to go through Babylonian territory.
And so the Babylonians become an immediately looming threat.
And then it's not long before 587, 586 Jerusalem falls to the Babylonians, temples destroyed
and the people are taken into exile.
in Babylon and Judah too is added to the Neobabalonean Empire.
The other thing Nebuchadnezzar does upon succeeding to the throne is he starts massive building
campaigns.
And this plays into a whole realm of Babylonian propaganda.
Remember, Nabopalacir, his father's whole movement started as this war of independence.
It was about restoring bow.
on to the greatness of the past. The Babylonian Empire at this point, the height of it was a thousand
years before this. I know it's just crazy to think about that. It's making like it was a
millennium ago, you guys. Yes. Yeah. Like that's when it was at its peak was a thousand years ago.
I mean, the closest thing is the way people still to this day talk about like the glory of Rome.
the show.
The show, right?
It's that kind of thing, like the Babylonian Empire...
and they're the heirs of that because they're Babylon, right? And so we're going to rebuild,
we're going to restore, we're going to get back there, right? Yeah, it would be like if Kierstarmor
suddenly got up and said, hey, let's make things like they were back during the period of Alfred the Great.
Yeah, you know, or William the Conqueror. Yeah. We don't talk about that guy.
the president did the other day. I don't know why, but look it up.
in the UK, he just starts talking about William the Coker and how cool of a name that is
being William the Coker. Anyway, well, whatever he calls him. So, uh, but so the the whole
sort of race on debt that started this whole process that ends in there being a neo-Babalone
and empire was the restoration of Babylon. And so that takes the form first and foremost
of a bunch of building projects. The first and
and most important of which is the renovation of the Esseguilla, which I pronounce correctly
this time.
I really heard of a pre-show, an old man.
So the renovation of the Esseguilla, the Esseguilla will talk about more in the second half, but
that's the original temple of Marduk in Babylon.
Right?
Marduk was historically the god of the city of Babylon, becomes the main god of the Babylonian
Empire, the sort of original temp-
in the city was the Esseguilla.
The Esseguilla, of course, in the original Babylonian Empire had become this massive great
thing after the fall of the old Babylonian Empire had fallen into various states of disrepair.
But the central elements of that temple, the Esseguilla, by the time you get to Devacate
Deser, are 2000 years old.
man and so he's restoring this ancient
2000 year old Temple of Marduk, right? Because that's sort of the central aspect of civil
and religious life for Babylon getting that back on its feet is obviously a big thing.
Second thing he does, he completes the building of Edim and Anki, the great Ziggurat of Babylon.
The big zig, which was a zig or a dedicated demarduk.
Then it started being built around 1400 BC in the Old Babylonian Empire.
So like 900 years or 800 years, 800 years before, they had started building the Ziggurat
and then the Old Babylonian Empire fell and they never finished it.
Okay.
So it's a devicate Ezra who finishes it.
keep in mind. We've talked about
in the past on the show, the different connections between the story of the tower of Babel and the Bronze Age collapse.
And this is part of that. There was in the city of Babylon from the period of time Moses would have lived until 600 BC.
There was a big giant unfinished tower sitting in the middle of the city of Babylon
So when anybody heard a story about a tower that didn't get finished because God intervened
That was called
Bobbie Lee
They're gonna be thinking of that big unfinished tower in Babylon, right? Yeah
I mean...
I mean, Babylon, this is all the same name.
Yeah.
But so he finally finishes it
and load behold, he didn't actually reach heaven.
There was just an alter to mark on top of it.
The remains of that also by the way,
are where they found that ritual bed
we talked about when we talked about Augs bed.
So special appearance by the giants.
There we go.
We mentioned the amurites earlier.
So, yes.
He also built the Ishtar Gate that was later rebuilt by Saddam Hussein.
Weird was the warning sign that showed us all that the rapture was going to happen in 1993.
Or yesterday.
Yeah, the case maybe.
We all remember the rapture from 1993.
I remember it from 1988.
And how the Great Tribulation ended in the year 2000.
And 19... Yeah, yeah.
So...
There are books. You can go look online. There are books with like Saddam Hussein's face of the Ishtar Gate on the cover. I know arguing that I'm not being positioned those really existed.
I am. Take me back.
But the Ishtar Gate, the original Ishtar Gate had beneath the layer of blue lacquer with a critter on it, which critter is a dragon, but a specific dragon who will talk about more in the second half.
Look, where is that logger?
It looks like a tall weasel though.
Kinda.
The, it could be like a really deformed grayhound.
Anyway.
Mmm.
Like chicken, a chicken mink hybrid.
So the, but the bricks under there were all stamped with Nebuchadnezzar's name.
one of them individually and you can go see them to this day.
It's still true. But also a bunch of them were stamped with the names of Assyrian kings. Meaning
Nebuchadnezzar sent people to tear down Assyrian monuments in and around Babylon.
Stamp those bricks with Nebuchadnezzar's name and then use them to build his building projects.
So he was enacting this sort of...
destruction and wiping away of the Assyrians, right, in these restorations.
The Ishtar Gate was the northern gate to the city of Babylon,
and the reason it's important and the reason why it was so decorative, as opposed to the other ones,
is that it was the ritual gate. So, when they did ritual processions for feasts and that kind of thing,
the pagan feasts, ritual processions, they went through that gate. That's why it was so elaborately decorated.
He also went to the...
far north, the northern edge of the fertile crescent, the northern edge of the Neobabalone
Empire, because he's worried about barbarians coming and raiding things, which was always
a worry, because it took so long, especially depending on what time of year it was to deploy
troops, that barbarians could raid a place and be gone before you could get anybody there
to do anything about it.
So he built two massive border walls.
up at the north. As far as we know, he was not able to get the barbarians to pay for them.
But he did build these border walls. He built a number of canals in and around the Euphrates.
He built a canal connecting the Tigris and Euphrates. He built a canal from the Euphrates that ran
through the city to irrigate things like the next building project we're going to talk about.
So he masterminded these massive irrigation projects.
And he built the hanging gardens of Babylon, one of the seven wonders of the ancient world.
There's been a lot of talk, I have to say this, there's been a lot of talk in the chat tonight
about Sid Meier's civilization.
So this is where all connects now, finally everybody, the hanging gardens of Babylon, which
is all built.
I hope.
Yes.
So the hanging gardens of Babylon, which was essentially sort of a ziggurat-like structure
and that it had steps, but then each of the steps.
had garden on it. So the idea was it was supposed to be a reconstruction of the garden of the gods on the mountain of the gods and
this required a feat of both building construction engineering and irrigation engineering.
Right, considering where it was to keep all of that alive.
And apparently from what ancient visitors say, they felt like having been there and in it.
that they had experienced being in the Garden of the God.
So that's why it's one of the seven wonders
of the ancient world,
because it was apparently amazingly impressive
for its day and technologically, right?
It's still pretty impressive to this day,
what he was able to do.
So, Nebuchadise Racomphlish is all this.
Nebuchadise Raventially dies in 562 BC.
Meaning he reigns for 43 years.
This is really impressive because the Neobabalone and Empire does not last that long.
Yeah.
Okay.
So if you take as the starting point of the Neobabalone and Empire, the beginning of Navajo
Palazza's revolt, then it was around from 626 BC to 549 BC, 77 years.
Yep.
If you take, which is probably...
more accurate, the Battle of Carcomish to be the beginning of the Babylonian Empire.
And then it ends at 549, then it was around for 56 years total.
Babylon the Great.
And Nebuchadnezzar was the emperor for 43 of them.
So he kind of is Babylon.
So right.
He yeah, he is it.
Right.
The Dio Pavilloni Empire is Nebuchadnezzar because...
It's only around after he dies for 13 years.
Yeah.
And then Cyrus the Great, the Persians take over.
Literally.
When the Democrats are died in 562 BC, who is immediately succeeded by his son, Amal Marduk,
we know there were some issues around the succession.
We don't know exactly what they were.
I don't...
know what they were. Well, sort of like with the Assyrians, the guy who won, rewrote the history.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. And so, Emma Marnock, what's he
with is like, it's the records are yes, he was the chosen heir of his father, not, but we know
things like he wasn't the first born son of a Democrat Ezra. Yeah. Right. So, there seems
There seems to be some kind of chaos right around the...
that briefly would never could desert eyes.
And Emil Marduk ends up being the emperor
of the neo-Babalonean empire for less than two years.
And then he's assassinated by one of his court officials.
So not a very secure succession at all.
And the last few emperors during those other 11 years
the video Babylonian Empire exists.
this are not around for very long and are not biologically related as far as we can tell
to Nebuchadnezzar or Neboplaser.
So once Nebuchadnezzar is off stage, the decline is swift in terms of the Empire.
So that's brief history of the Neobabelonian Empire Nebuchadnezzar.
I have an interesting definition of brief.
And we skipped it.
A thousand years in between.
Yeah, yeah.
Mostly.
So in our second half, we're going to talk about Babylonian religion.
I'm so excited.
All right.
Well, you've wasted a good, perfectly good 80 minutes of your life listening to this first
half of this episode of Lord of Spirits.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
For centuries, Byzantine music has sustained Orthodox worship around the world.
the Singh John Kuckosellis Institute of the surgical
Arts offers online classes in notation, theory, and practice, and free classes in the
Churches, with a faculty led by John Michael Boyer, author of the acclaimed book Byzantine
chant of the received tradition.
Registration is open now for classes in September at kukuzelvist.net.
That's k-o-u-k-o-u-z-e-l-i-s.net.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the father Andrew Stephen Damick and father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question...
Call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
As an MC, West's line readings did not seem fully rehearsed.
He sounded like an actor who was nearly but not quite off-book, suggesting the proper emotional
intonations as often as he truly tried to sell them.
This had an unexpectedly intriguing effect, perhaps because so many of the vocals on his recent
Albums have
felt flat and disengaged. Another passage from the ancient texts of Rolling Stone's
review of Kanye West's Nebuchadnezzar. I don't know, this review is just the gift
that keeps on giving, I think. I mean, at least he had named it Nebuchadnezzar.
Should have called it Nabu protect the Mule. See, I would have shown up for that.
elaborate. That could be the great, I mean that sounds like a show too.
protect the mule. Yes, right. Like that has like showtune written all over it. But yeah, yeah,
something about a bright holding golden haze on the meadow. I don't know.
At a mule anyway. So yeah, religion now, right? Not that we haven't talked about anything religious
just so far, because these things are not separate, but we're going to sort of.
focus on Babylonian religion and the figure who for obvious reasons looms large over Babylonian religion is Marduk
who we've talked before we have this idea today of Pantheons
The Greek one being the one people are most most familiar with but then maybe Egyptian ones up
We think of pantheons of gods and we kind of think of
them like the Justice League or the Avengers or something, right?
Like it's the collection of these gods.
They all have different abilities and powers and stuff and they team up and and that pagan
sort of worship to this group of gods.
And as we mentioned many times before on the show, that's not how any of this worked.
That the reality is individual locations, locals, cities, villages, even just geographical
features like springs and groves had
and gods associated with them by pagans. And so each locality has a god or two, right,
that they they're involved in worshiping. And quote unquote, pantheons are things that happen
when you start getting larger socio-political units than the city. So if you listen to the episode
or I read everybody bedtime stories.
And he listened to the Memphite theology, that was a good example.
So that's a text that comes from the period when upper and lower Egypt were united.
And so the gods that were worshipped in the cities that upper Egypt and the gods that
were worshipped in the cities in lower Egypt were sort of all brought together.
And said to be related to each other in various ways.
once for more prominent cities became father.
and less prominent cities became sons, right, et cetera.
Connected cities became siblings, right?
But that was a way in sort of narrative form,
in sort of myth form, to express what we would today call
the socio-political relationships.
Not that that was a primitive way of doing it,
they just saw everything, and we're gonna see this a lot
in this half of the show.
Everything that's happening on earth.
is connected to things that are going on in the spiritual realm.
On earth as it isn't heaven.
That they mirror each other.
Right.
And so, Marduc originally is not the head of a pantheon or the member of a pantheon.
This is yet another problem with the goofy thesis we already tore apart in the Storm Gods episode
that Yahweh the God of Israel was at one point a quote-unquote member of a pantheon.
Right. That's not a thing.
But Marduk is none of that. Marduk is just the God who is worshiped in the settlement
then village then city of Babylon. The name Marduk originally was MR Utu, which doesn't
look much like Marduk or sound much like Marduk, but we'll explain here in a second.
R. U.T. is Sumerian.
means the calf of Utu. Utu, calf meaning like young bull. So the the
bull of heaven we associate bulls with the divine. So the calf means the son
right of the bull god, right. And Utu was the Sumerian name for the sun god. The
the Acadian Seminic name for the same sun god was Shemesh.
We have talked before back of the Melchidazadek episode.
We talked about the fact that Shemesh,
the Semitic Sun God is the God that was worshiped in Jerusalem
before David took it. And unfortunately, after Solomon.
Yeah. Until King Josiah.
So what's interesting about this is this is this is Marduk's original name,
which associates him and
the son of the sun god who is this bull god, but in none of the later stories about Marduk,
is he associated it in any way with the sun god?
See, but this is his original name. And so the going theory is that we know that very early
and its existence. So we're talking about third millennium BC, 2000's BC.
that Babylon as a settlement and as a small city was kind of a dependency of the nearby city of Sipar.
And Sipar as a Sumerian city was Utu, Sumerian name, Shemesh, the sun god, is the god that was worshiped at Sipar.
So, that being his original name may reflect...
that relationship between Sipar and Babylon. Right? That Babylon at that point as a
small town is a dependency of the bigger city of Sipar and so the god of that
town is seen as the sun of the god of the bigger city. Right? And then that
relationship obviously changes very radically as Babylon becomes a bigger city
and becomes ascended and so that whole relationship gets lost to his
history. Right. But so, Amaru Utu, over time, we're talking about over the course of
like a thousand years here, becomes Amaru Utu becomes Maru Utuq. So the initial
ag it's dropped. Right. So, say, Amaru you have Mar, say, Utu you have Utuq, Maru Utuq.
then becomes martouk and then martouk. Yeah.
So by the time we get to, you know, the time of Hamarabi, he's Marduk.
So Babylon, as we mentioned, starts out as this sort of backwater town, right?
And Marduk was originally an agrarian God. He was a god of farmers at that time.
and one of the primary symbols for him in that early
period, but that hangs on even to when he is considered like the high god of the Babylonian and
neopabalone empire, he still has a spade as one of his symbols. You'll see spades in the iconography,
right? There were likely spades in the temple, right? That were held on to from this point of
Now I said to give another example of this, I said that
That relationship with the Sun God was kind of lost it wasn't totally lost because even all the way down to the neo-Babolonian Empire
When they did
Precessions for Marduk they had the sort of Sun
They had the Sun iconography that they carried on polls
Hmm even though Marduk was not a Sun God so there were ways to it so
What you find is
religious ritual including
pagan religious ritual was in the ancient world one of the best ways of preserving these things.
Much better than like the histories, the annals of kings, those get edited all the time,
like deliberately whereas religious rituals and traditions, everyone has the attitude in the
the ancient world that the more ancient they are, the better.
So they're loath to change.
anything, even if they don't understand it anymore. Right? Because sometimes we have,
you can see this with the Greeks, when you read like Plato and Aristotle's understandings
of certain ancient religious things, like we know they're wrong, because we have sources
they did from those ancient times that they didn't have available to them. And so it's clear
that the original significance had been t-
totally lost by the by the four century BC among the Greeks and they're just kind of.
They've either heard some explanation that somebody made up for it or their.
Or they're making it up themselves. This happens all the time by the way still to this day in the Orthodox liturgy.
I can't tell you how many amazing theological explanations I've heard for the fanning of the gifts.
which I hate to break all your hearts, but that was to keep bugs away.
What they say. I mean, there's nothing, but there's like nothing.
Theologians, the rich, are nice and they're fine.
Right. There's nothing wrong with attaching these other, these other meanings, you know,
perfectly. A lot of the church fathers did that. I could have nothing wrong with that.
Right. But my point is just that there was an original reason. Yeah.
That original reason gets lost such that people don't know it, right? Right.
But they keep doing it.
it. Right? Even though in some cases they may not know why they're doing it. And then these
other explanations for it come up later. Right? So that still happens with religious ritual.
But religious ritual because we don't change it because we want to keep the most ancient forms
possible, it preserves all of these things through time amazingly well. That's one of the
the importance is when you're studying ancient cultures of studying the actual religious
ritual.
because you get more accurate windows into earlier stages than you do from histories that
are edited and propagandized, right, later on.
So all that said, so Mardek starts out as this agrarian god, the spade symbol, right?
He's about farms, he's about bringing the rain in its season, male fertility.
So you get some storm god stuff.
He's not a storm god proper originally, but he is connected with the rain and with
Propfertility.
And what would later become the Esseguilla that we mentioned,
sort of the original temple for Marduk in Babylon is built around 2500 BC.
So, 4,500 years ago, 4,500 years before present, give or take.
There's a shrine built there for
Marduk. So then we mentioned historically the Amuru come in, they settle in and around Babylon,
they build up Babylon, begin the old Babylonian empire. Babylon rises to prominence as a city,
so does Marduk, therefore, among other gods, and we start to see certain transformations. So
So one of the earliest is
that Marduk gets a wife whose name is either Zapar Nitu or Sarpannet. There was a village
just outside of Babylon. As Babylon became a city, it had farming villages around it that were
dependencies, and one of those dependent villages was Zarpann. And Zapar Nitu was the goddess of that
little village and she becomes...
because of the rise of prominence of Babylon
and it being a dependency, she becomes
Marduk's wife in terms of the stories.
And originally, she seemed, how?
I was gonna say, I keep waiting at some point
for one of these names, finally, that somebody's gonna meet.
Some person or place is gonna be named Zardaz.
Cause it just, yeah.
Anyway, they won't be great.
But so Zarpan Zarpanitu originally was a goddess
associated with pregnancy. So they would go to the shrine in this village and make offerings of
this kind of thing when women were trying to get pregnant or had a difficult pregnancy. Right.
And this kind of thing. But as Marduk rises in prominence, becomes the most important God of the
old Babylonian empire. She also then rises in prominence and becomes very closely associated with
David
nation. Okay. And remember, remember the Amorites, right?
They were the ones who are building really the old Babylonian
empire. Remember, we've said many times on the show, who come
to chat some giants again, peeking their heads in, that their
claim to power was that they held the secret wisdom delivered by
the gods before the flood.
Yeah. Right. So it's not Marduk, the male God who's seen as the repository of that wisdom. It comes to be his wife.
Zeppernito. Right. So remember in the book of Enoch, the women received from the watchers, right, the wisdom,
divination and all of these things. So the repository this is separate.
to this goddess and as the as a as a as a is a is a is expanded right goes from being a shrine to
being a temple to being a big temple complex and Zeppelin II has become Bardock's wife she gets a
section of that temple complex in Babylon and her section of the temple complex is referred to
as the house of the secrets of heaven and the netherworld.
Wow. So it's the name and next album of my my side project band of
Ugrinick Deathkurs. That's the secret secrets of having in the
another world, which is a teacher you can buy for the yeah. Yeah.
That's the connection here. Right. Like that that's her part of the
tells the repository, right?
The one who's sleeping with Marduk, right?
That's...
the repository for the secrets of heaven and the netherworld. They're the temple in Babylon.
Also during this time they build a throne of Marduk in the Essegilla. In the Essegilla
What they have thrown there is what was already probably about a thousand year old
idol of Marduk.
And it already sort of ancient idol of Marduk, which was believed to be Marduk.
And Marduk is there with his dragon pal, Moussusu.
Oh, yeah.
The tall Wizu.
Moussusu, who's all over the Ishtar gate.
That's Moussusu.
Who's just asking to become a Disney comedy sidekick, I think.
I can see
I feel like he is.
Is it either?
No.
Like, they do some homerabi animated movie.
I'm trying to remember the name of the dragon,
the silly dragon sidekick in.
Now I'm blanking on the film with the brave Chinese girl.
Oh, Mulan.
Mulan.
Yeah.
I'm trying to remember the name of the sound off in the chat
there.
Tell us who's Mulan's dragon sidekick.
everybody I'm sure you all know right.
top your head. But remember this is a this is a very common motif in ancient idolatry.
It's moush shu. It is moush shu. But not moush shusu. No, not moush shusu, but I mean they
could be related kind of close. Yeah, yeah. There's some kind of nerd working on those movies.
Yeah, yeah, but this is a common motif in ancient idolatry
where the god is depicted with a dragon or serpent as a representative of wisdom.
This goes all the way down to if you look at the early statuary of Athena in Athens,
she usually has a serpent next to her.
Well, and even the the holosclepius imagery, right?
You got this...
Right, it's twined around the staff.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So this is even more ancient that Mushusu there with Marduk, right?
Right, this ancient dragon representing the 8th-
ancient to Louvian wisdom. So I hope as we're describing this right, you're making
the connections and seeing some of the motifs and things we've talked about in the past
and in the Bible and how the Bible inverts a lot of these things.
So as Babylon rises in prominence and becomes sort of the the locus of the old
We see the usual pattern of assimilation.
Meaning other gods are sort of assimilated into Marduk.
They say, well, the god of this city who's named that, but that's really Marduk.
And then also assimilation in the sense of like we just talked about with the family relationships.
Right. So, oh, well, this is Naboo is Marduk's son.
A is Marduk.
Father, right, who's sort of the ancient most high God is the Father of Marduk, right?
And so that a civilization takes the form of the gods of all these various cities being
put in place, right?
So, you know, Uruk, they're worshiping Aya, Uruk is a more ancient city than Babylon,
but now Babylon is more prominent.
So Marduk becomes the son of the god of Uruk, who is now sort of ascended as his father
Wayne's
off in old age, right? These kind of ideas, right, within the myth structure. And remember
Aya and Inki are two names. This is again, Akkadian and Sumerian names for the same god.
Now an interesting thing, an interesting thing that happens in Babylon, in both the old Babylonian
Empire and of the Neo Babylonian Empire.
that when the emperors list their titles, right, we already talked about some of those titles,
like Father Andrew mentioned, you know, how we're always the king of the four corners of the world,
they look at answers, the king of the universe, they all use king of sumer and a cod,
right, whoever united, Mesopotamia and all this, but the first title they always list in the long
list of titles.
The first title they always list is Governor of Babylon, like Governor of the City of Babylon,
which seems weirdly primitive.
King of the Universe, but Governor of Babylon.
Yeah.
Yes, I also handle administrative duties in the City of Babylon.
And I rule the Universe.
But what that is, is that is an ancient Babylonian
tradition where they call themselves the governor of the city of Babylon because they hold that
Marduk is the king of Babylon. Yeah, so the god is the king of Babylon. So the emperor, the universe
is just the sidekick in Babylon proper, right to the god, right, for his son or whatever. Yeah.
And this, that sort of strategy.
In tradition, you see reflected, we talked about this in Isaiah and Ezekiel in terms of the passage is dealing with the fall of the devil
More on that to come here soon
Where the Bible will talk about the human king as the prince like say the prince of tire and refer to
Bale as the king of tire
Yeah
Right, so that's a practice that gets picked up in the Bible to distinguish those two
Right
So, uh, Nebuchadnezzar I, who we mentioned last time.
So not our Nebuchadnezzar, but the first one in the 12th century BC, the one is at the
very tail end of the Old Babylonian Empire.
We mentioned already he was sort of the last gasp of trying to salvage and keep going
old Babylonian Empire as it was collapsing.
And he was the last one to try and kind of reassert Babylonian culture.
Things had gotten so bad by that point that the city of Babylon was sacked by the Ilamites
who were a tribal group who ended up settling in Mesopotamia.
But the Ilamites had sacked Babylon and they stole the idol.
Thank you, Melody.
You're welcome.
From the Essegilla.
from from the esegila
So they made off with their
God. Very embarrassing. If you're trying to keep the whole empire thing going, right?
Not a good sign. But, but Nebuchadnezzar I still gave it a go. He managed to defeat the
Eloise and get it back. And there was a reinstallation. And there's a whole series of
Texas from that.
re-installation were sort of further aggrandizing Marduk, but they couldn't hold it together and the old
Babylonian empire collapsed. So there's a few texts out there and most of these texts, two out of three,
which Meatloaf told us wasn't bad. Of them, we have in their Assyrian form.
So be aware that's reflected.
The Assyrian attitude toward Babylon is kind of reflected in some of these.
The first one and the one that folks listening may have heard of at some point is the Anuma
Ailesh.
The Anuma Ailesh is mainly famous because of stupid documentaries that claim that Genesis
this plagiar-
the creation story from it. We'll describe that creation story here and you tell me if you think
that that's just exactly like Genesis. Interacted with Sure has dragons. Yes,
dragons. Sure, it interacted with the story, right, and inverted some things in fact, but
But plagiarizes not just strong, it's ridiculous, preposterous.
But anyway.
So there was a major Assyrian festival called the Akitu Festival.
It seems to have been taken over and repurposed by the Neobabalonian Empire during its short existence.
But that is itself likely because the Assyrians stole it from earlier Mesopotamian cultures.
As we mentioned, they kind of made a pastiche of Mesopotamian culture for their own culture.
So in the
In the Enuma-Alish, we get a pretty good characterization of Marduk that's reflected in a lot of other
smaller texts involving ritual texts and stuff that we have regarding Marduk.
He is referred to as Savage Yet Relenting.
Okay.
So Marduk is Savage like he just likes killing things and reckons stuff.
That's really he's very angry all the time.
But every once in a while, he will relent.
So I guess you could kind of say he's merciful in the sense that
sometimes he calms down and doesn't go, you know, sometimes he just beats you have to death.
Right.
I mean, this right an abusive relationship.
It reminds me of my favorite old Don Rickles joke.
Ha ha!
I did not see that sentence coming.
Yeah.
Don Rickles said, you used to say Frank, Frank's an actress saved my life once.
And they'd say, oh really how?
And he'd say, he said, all right, boys, he's had enough.
So it's that kind of thing.
Right.
Wow.
That's, you know, yeah, he'll relit.
So like when we find these prayer texts to Marduk.
They're in the context of sort of anything bad happening in the world was because Marduk was ticked
If to the point of someone is sick
Someone is sick and maybe dear death that's because Marduk's mad and it's just he's killing them
Okay, and so
Literally the prayers to Marduk are like please for mercy
Right like come on man. He's had enough
right like it.
Nice.
Please stop.
We know you're back.
But man just calm down. We don't want no trouble like it's all good. We'll offer you some sacrifices and stuff
I like told all religions are the same. Yes, exactly. Yeah
So if you're Christianity bears any resemblance to that I have bad news for you. You're not a Christian. You're a pagan
Like our first sorry Calvinists for the episode. I did not say that
You said that.
I will, you know.
Right, but so, right, he is, Martin is like a God of wrath, who occasionally relents from
his wrath.
He is not a God of love, right, who disciplines and chastises, right, as a loving father,
right?
These are very different concepts of who God is.
As we'll see is the story of the Anumin Elish plays out as well.
So the new A-list describes the creation of the world.
So it starts out there are two gods, two sort of primordial elder gods.
Apsu and Tiamat.
They're both dragons.
They're also both oceans.
Okay, Tiamat is the ocean above.
This guy, Opsu is the ocean below.
Actually, that's reversed.
Opsu is the ocean above.
Tiamat is the ocean below.
like this.
C, right?
Because she's chaos, probably real chaos.
So, Opsu and Tiamat, the sky and the sea.
Notice no dry land, OK?
Do you see all the connections to Genesis?
Like there's a water's above water below no dry land.
See, it's just like Genesis, exactly.
Just like that.
Except dragons and two gods.
Dragon.
Um, so, that's, so, uh, I'm sure with Tiamat, uh,
a 4-in-a-k.
and produce the other gods, right?
The sort of regular gods.
So they make baby gods.
And then Opsu decides these gods are,
these god kids of mine are making too much noise.
They're super irritating.
I've had enough of them.
I'm going to kill them all.
Do you remember that part of Genesis 1, right?
That's on me.
It's my favorite bit.
time.
going to kill them all, but he's back again gets the first born son of Opsu gets
wind of it and goes and kills his father first. Beautiful story. I think Kronos and Rino's
think, Zeus and Cronos, right? We're drawing from the same wells here, okay?
And then Aya, of course, has a son, Marduk.
Marduk decides to go and kill his grandma.
Wait, why?
Because he's a savage.
That's why.
I mean, at least the Greek guys have the decency to just kill their dads and grandfathers
and stuff.
Yeah.
And he goes after grandma who happens to be a chaos serpent, but still.
Right, still.
It's still his grandma.
But Marduk being a savage goes, kills grandma.
and then makes the dry land of the world out of her corpse, out of her carcass,
and the drops of her blood form humans, accidentally.
Whoops.
So I mean, Genesis 1 almost exactly.
Carbon copy plagiarism, anyway.
So the Anuma-Alish
then ends with Marduk acquiring his 50 names.
Ooh.
And these 50 names are not just, you know,
random titles of self-aggrandizement.
But these are the titles of other gods.
And so in the text, these other gods
voluntarily sort of hand over their titles.
They're like, man, Marduk, that grammar killing
with some of the
best grandma murder and I ever seen. I you could have my title buddy. I just have to say that we
we have a lot of creative people who listen to this podcast and so I'm just putting out a challenge
for you creative people to take Paul Simons there must be 50 ways to lead your lover and apply it
to the 50 names of Marduk and his grandma killing savagery. I mean it's just gotta work. This is
I thought you were going for some kind of design.
for a Mardek Kildar grandma t-shirt.
A little too, oh, I don't know.
But no, no, no, I want music, I want music.
So putting that out there to the world.
Yeah, there must be 50 ways to kill you.
I don't know, but anyway.
50 names for good old Mardek.
Yeah.
50 ways to name your Mardek.
So yeah, I've got the good old brother right now.
They just relinquished.
their titles. One of whom is Enlil. We'll get more to Marduk and Enlil here in a minute.
But what's going on here, right, is what we talked about. So these other gods are the gods of the
other cities that are in the Old Babylonian Empire. Right, so the idea is that not that like
like Marduk has, you know, and Babylon, therefore.
or have enslaved these other cities, but no, Babylon is just so great, just so amazing that
all these other cities want to be a part of it.
And the gods of all those cities are just so amazed by how awesome Lee Savage, Marduk,
is that they willingly, right, like no, no, no, no, no, no, no, we're, we're, we're
worship him more, right? Like he's the guy, right? So that's
way of encoding that right into this religious text, this religious text is read and recited
at that a key to festival that we mentioned. So the reading and reciting of this is part
of this annual religious observance right and feast related to Marduk. The second text
we have that focuses on Marduk is also what associated with the Akidu festival. This
This one is very clearly...
a Syrian edited, shall we say.
That's, it is referred to as the ordeal of Marduk,
and it's all about how Marduk was sort of captured
and imprisoned by the other gods.
Especially Asher.
Oh.
Well, well, well.
And so the Assyrians
read and enacted this story
literally every year at the Akidu Festival.
Part of that was the subjugation of Babylon, right?
The idea that all of that stuff from Old Babylon is now sort of their possession.
Yeah, because what happens to the God is what's happening to the people who worship that
God.
Yeah.
And there's some evidence that there are some later maybe Neobabalone inversions of the
story where Bardock ends up escaping that are probably related to the re-assendency of
babble on in the knee.
Babylonian Empire. So, why did I make that point about Enlil in particular out of all the 50 gods?
So, Enlil was, if we're talking about the Old Babylonian Empire or and the Neobatelian Empire,
Enlil was one of the previous most high gods who was sort of superseded by Marduk.
Okay. And because Babylon came into
prominence and little drops off.
It is no longer the big guy.
In Isaiah, the text we already mentioned
about the fall of the devil,
that talks about where it talks about
Hillel Ben-
Hello Ben-
Shacar in the Hebrew,
which famously St. Jerome translated into Latin
as Lucifer son of the morning star.
I'm not sure if you're
going to be able to do that.
Um, uh,
Originally,
Hello, Ben Chicare was a reference to
N. Will.
So it's a how they'll fall in
O'Loucah for a son of the morning.
It's originally.
How are they'll fall in and will
son of the morning star Venus?
Right.
Um,
Yeah, yeah, hello, hello.
So, Isaiah there is using this Mesopotamian story.
He's writing in the Assyrian era, he's prophesied, is using this as an image of the fall of the devil.
In the same way that M little, right, used to be the big guy who everybody tells it now
or right.
Now is ignominy.
And this is one of the big points that there's the famous verse that sometimes when we talk
about the idea of monotheism, right, where Isaiah says regarding Yahweh, the God of Israel,
Yahweh says, you know, before me there was none and after me there will be no other,
right?
That's not really a reference to polytheism there.
That's a reference to the idea of succession.
Right.
the idea that there wasn't another God.
who was the most high God before Yahweh, the God of Israel.
And there's not gonna be another one
who comes along and displaces him.
It's always an eternally him.
Unlike Enlil, unlike Marduk, unlike Zeus, unlike Chronos,
unlike all of the Bale, right?
Yeah.
You know, with the succession myth that's everywhere, right?
So Enlil is the one who Marduk in particular displaces.
And so that has that biblical relevance
And so then last note, last text that deals with Marduk is a text called the Epic of Era,
the RRA. And the Epic of Era tells this kind of weird story where this God era comes and kind of talks
Mark's Marduk into vacating his throne and going and hanging out in the Netherworld for a while.
Well, hey man, the other world's great this season.
Why don't you go, take a break to check it out.
It's cold outside.
Yeah, so Marduk does, right?
And while he's gone, Erra, and sort of takes his throne,
and Erra stinks at the whole God thing.
Oh, like everything is just bad on Earth
when Erra thinks there's like plagues everywhere
and famines and stuff and everything kind of starts
to collapse and fall apart.
Straight of duties.
And then sort of Martin gets wind of how bad things are going.
And so yes, to sort of come back and be like, air.
Come on, bro, right?
Yes, like I'm back and take his throat again.
Right.
And, and ready to get everything back in order.
And what this seems to be is it seems to be a mythic way of describing this sort of
Interregnum between the old Babylonian and neo-Babalonean Empire?
Hmm, like...
Where did where did Marta go?
Oh, right. He was he was on on vacation. He was yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And you saw how bad
everything got there. How much everything stunk when he was gone, right? So isn't it good
that he's back? Right. You should all be extra happy. But the element here that's that's
important to point out is that is this then passage through the underworld that Marta
makes. So you get a kind of catholic
Marduk here. And that's one of the things that helps because very late in the Neobabalone
in period, and then in the post Neobabalone in period. So Marduk doesn't have the same
prominence under the Persians, but the Persians, and we're going to do an episode at some
point here, maybe even the next one that airs about Cyrus and the Persian Empire. But the
The Persians took a very different approach to empire and that they let everyone in the
the chair.
territories they controlled keep their local traditions and religious practices.
So, even though Babylon is not the center of empire anymore after the fall of the neo-Babalonian
empire, Marduk worship and Babylon continues, right?
It continues to be a place, right?
It continues to practice these things down to Rember Burosis who we mentioned last time,
who's writing in Greek and who is a priest.
He's a priest of Bell Marduk.
Because what happens later,
toward the end of the Neobabalonean period,
is that Marduk and Bale start to assimilate together.
Yeah.
Bale being the form of, the Babylonian dialect form of Bale.
As you can see, different vocalization, same consonants.
And you get Bale Marduk.
One of the things that facilitates that
is the idea of a Catholic tradition associated with Marduk,
just like their Catholic traditions associated with.
with a bell, better.
Yeah. All right. Well, um, yeah, that's the end of the second half of this episode.
On we have mentioned nebuchadnezzar, so we're not completely sticking with our normal form
of waiting until the third half. But, but this is the nebuchadnezzar episode.
So we're going to take our second break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymek and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of spirits.
Give them a call.
at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of the
epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
But Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world in St. Paul the Ferris.
the
Jewish Apostle to all nations.
Father Stephen D. Young surveyes Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the
holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's epistles, which
deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism, D. Young hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and helped the reader reassess Saint Paul in his historical
Con.
available now at store.AncientFace.com. Again, that is store.AncientFace.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and
Father Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
radio. It's hard to overstate just how strange this will seem in the future.
The most overexposed, overexamined musician of the century, who had broke clearing samples
then got rich again selling shoes, booking a famous outdoor venue to stage an opera that
is more or less a straight reading of the Old Testament during which he never appears
in the flesh.
It was not strictly speaking effective art, too muddled, and off the cuff to work as a
narrative piece, too linear, to read as a performance installation.
Merchandise sales did not seem to be a focal point as they have been at nearly all of West
other 2019 appearances. As the opera ended, some in the audience shuffled and texted and talked
among themselves. Others held their arms in the sky in an extended moment of praise. West is not
the first generational talent to pivot to religion mid-career, but neither Dylan nor Prince's
fits of religiosity were quite so strangely realized, so massively articulated. And that once again
The Rolling Stone Review of Kanye West's Opera N-
kidnether. Did you go see that show? Father Steven? I am young by the way according to that commercial.
I'm just young. The young. The young. The young. I'm not the younger anymore. I'm
and
another old
it's true it's true
sad many so it's sad
yep
where's all the calls
I mean, we had some we got a lazy call screener who's just telling everybody they're off
topics.
So he doesn't have your off topic.
You're off topic.
Yeah.
Good luck.
You're fun.
What gives?
I'm calling people out.
I know.
Somebody must have called.
Yeah.
We're not getting anything at the moment, but it's fishy.
Well, you know, when we do the conference here in a week or so, this is a
Yeah, about a week it's going to be live Q&A so you'll get your fill.
No, one week from now exactly we will be doing the live Q&A.
That is true.
In person, in the flesh, they can throw rotten vegetables.
If they, well, please don't do that, actually.
I'm realizing that people would do that.
Preferably paper money.
It hurts less when you throw it.
Yes.
No quarters, you know, paper money only.
Right, so we just took a tour through Babylon.
religion. Um, how about some Bible? What do you think? This is kind of a Bible. I'm
attracted by feedback. What would for a phone call?
Still not see it any of the call board. People are they're just too intimidated by your father's
We have lines open people, right? It's just intimidated. Uh, yeah. Anyway, so uh, yeah. So
So this final
this third and final half of the show. We're going to be talking about all that stuff we just
talked about the first two halves, places where that shows up in the Bible, other than the few that
we kind of hit along the way. And there are a couple of places where the Battle of Carcamish
in 605. Get mentioned in the...
in the Bible. One of them is Jeremiah 46 verse 2, which is just kind of a bare mention that it happened.
Right. But we get a little more pertinent info in Second Chronicles 35 verses 23-24.
So in this, starting with verse 20, after all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple,
NECCO, there he is again, King of Egypt.
went up to fight at Carcomish on the Euphrates, and just saw him out to meet him.
But he sent end-voiced to him saying,
what have we to do with each other, King of Judah?
I'm not coming against you this day,
but against the house with which I am at war,
and God has commanded me to hurry,
see supposing God who is with me, unless he destroy you.
Nevertheless, Josiah did not turn away from him,
but disguised himself in order to fight with him.
He did not listen to the words of Neco from the mouth of God
but came to fight in the plane of Meghito,
and the archers sh-
King Josiah and the king said to his servants, take me away from him badly wounded.
So his servants took him out of the chariot and carried him in his second chariot and brought
him to Jerusalem and he died and was buried in the tombs of his fathers.
All due to Andrew's slum mourned for Josiah.
Not a great ending for a pretty good king, one of the best.
No, like he's one of the like he had David, like the two good kings.
Yeah, very much.
Is really juta. Are there something that's up?
that are relatively good in various ways, right?
And some who repent and different things,
Solomon repents before he dies, Manasseh, Hezekiah.
But in terms of just like held up as sort of models,
Josiah was kind of it for most of his life.
He destroyed idols that had been in Jerusalem
and in and around the temple since Solomon's day.
He recovered the book of the law.
good things he did. But not perfect. And that ends up being how he meets his end. So what
had happened is behind the scenes. Remember what we were talking about leading up, this
is the Battle of Carcomish leading up to the Battle of Carcomish. Remember the Assyrians
of the Egyptians had had this pact. That's not aggression pact that we mentioned.
treaty. And the Assyrians, as we also mentioned, had destroyed the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
And they had taken a shot at, remember, at Judah and Jerusalem in particular, and had the
most of their army slaughtered by the angel of the Lord overnight. Yes, that's the
quote unquote pre-incarnate Christ who said.
Yeah, yeah, deal with it folks.
That's how he shows up in Revelation too.
So by the way, it looks like we are getting some calls coming in.
I'm just going to see what they're all right.
What they're so yeah, clear.
I mean, this is the first time I carry call that you've actually are really like calling out the
uncalling.
Yes.
So after that one attempt, though, there hadn't been further attempts.
and the reason that
had been further attempts by the Assyrians to take Judah is that Judah had made certain
treaties and agreements with Egypt.
Okay.
All right.
Since you let me finish this and they will do it.
Yeah, finish it.
You're going to say, yeah, go ahead.
So, uh, God had told them not to do this.
Right.
God had said, look, I'm the one who protected you from the Assyrians in the last time.
Not the Egyptians.
You don't want to be making treaties with the pagan nations.
That's what got Solomon into trouble.
The first place he says, you don't want to do this, right?
And this is going to be a problem all the way through the safe, there's going to be the
same problem when the Babylonian show up, right?
The Jeremiah is going to have to deal with where they want to make deals with Egypt, right?
Thinking Egypt will protect them.
And God says no.
And so this gets to the point where Josiah, because those, King Josiah, because those, who
It was a saint in the other excerpt.
Because of those agreements, he feels like he's sort of obligated by those agreements to go and fight with
Pharaoh Neco inventor of the wafer at the Battle of Carcomish
Right, I don't know why I left it at a third time that somehow it gets me every day
But right like at the Battle of Carcomish and so in this passage that you read in second Chronicles 35
God goes so far as to speak
prophetically through the Pharaoh of Egypt.
He gets it.
His demon worshipper.
Yes.
So the Pharaoh tells him, God is saying to you, do not come out and fight with me.
Right?
The guy who the agreement is with is telling him to stay home.
But King Josiah feels obligated, possibly by honor or something else, or fear of the Babylonians
or the Assyrians.
He goes out to fight anyway.
and ends up being killed in battle,
and that ends up being the end of
St. Anne King, Josiah.
Now, who's our caller?
All right, we have Caleb calling from,
well, I assume it's Michigan, it's MI.
Yeah, why don't you just speak for yourself.
Caleb, welcome to Lord of Spirits Podcast.
Hello, can you hear me?
We hear you. Can you hear us?
I think back in here, just fine.
Yes, I am from the Michigan.
I think actually there was another Caleb from Michigan,
from one of you other episodes,
but he's from the upper peninsula.
I'm from the lower peninsula.
You're not a troll.
You live below the bridge.
That's correct.
I live next to a bridge.
OK.
Close.
I take the troll toll.
Even trolls move into the suburbs.
Yes.
There's various troll kids.
as well. That's right. That's right. That's right.
Yes. So, man, I don't know.
What's on your mind, Caleb? All right. So you, there may not be a much of an
answer to this. So if you don't have it, just don't worry about it. But
on an episode, I can't remember because I've been this sounds good.
There's I just I've been listening to like dozens more than dozens of episodes.
I think I've finally caught up on the entire...
show up to this point from starting like a few months back.
On one of the episodes, a while back,
and the response to a different question, father to young,
you mentioned that you had, you mentioned off-candidly,
like not in any kind of detail that the Bronze Age collapse
might have something to do with the Tower of Babel.
Like, as I may, I don't know.
I was curious as to what the
was and I guess now that we're talking about Babylon, it might. And I think you mentioned
the Bronze Age collapse earlier. So maybe there's that I don't know if you have any further
explanation of that.
Yeah, very on topic. I'm actually trying to get Father Stephen to do a whole episode
on the Bronze Age collapse. Maybe we will. Yeah, so yeah, I mean, lay it out, Father, what's
the deal with the Abble and the Bronze Age collapse?
So what I have suggested is that the tower room...
Bable story in Genesis 10 and 11 is the story of the Bronze Age collapse from a spiritual perspective.
So what do you have in the narrative in Genesis?
You have the story of how after the flood, right?
So we have the things that happened before the flood that brought about the flood, right?
involving the Nephilim, involving all those things, evil and wickedness.
And then Genesis tells us that after the flood, this begins again.
The named person who seems to be one of the new giants is Nimrod, which, etymologically,
is the same name as the Mesopotamian God and Nurtah.
So there's a connection to Mesopotamia there.
global civilization that's described then, that is building towards the same level in
kinds of evil that we're going on before the flood.
culminates with the building of this tower, the Ziggurat, in a place called Babel, Bobbi Lee,
Babylon. And that tower never
gets finished because God comes down and disperses the nations, breaks up that world civilization
and disperses it.
Okay?
So that's the story we get told in Genesis.
Historically when we're talking about the Old Babylonian Empire, we have a worldwide
empire that's facilitating worldwide trade, named Babylon, that was built.
think a ziggurat that they never managed to finish at a manonki, that claimed to be
the repository, claimed to still possess the, quote unquote, wisdom from before the flood,
to be recreating the pre-flood civilization.
They claimed that, ruled over by people identified biblically the amyrites as giants.
who then have their global civilization smashed and never finished their tower?
Right? So it seems to me there's a very, very direct correspondence between the story
Genesis is telling and what we know historically happened to Babylon in the Bronze Age
collapse and all of these very direct points of connection. But what Genesis is doing
is it's giving us the spiritual perspective on this historic
events. That it wasn't just happenstance, it wasn't just climate change or the migration of
peoples or mismanagement or whatever that caused the fall, that it was God's doing to prevent the
world from becoming as evil as it had once before. And that therefore the loss of the old Babylonian
empire, just like the loss of the pre-flood civilization, was not this great loss to humanity and
and this thing to be mourned and this thing to attempt.
to recreate over and over again in the future.
But rather, something that was terrible and horrible
and was destroyed in judgment by God.
And this is why Babylon still has the resonance
it does in the New Testament
as the apostles are looking at Rome
and seeing Rome as old Babylon happening again,
which is the pre-flood civilization happening again.
Right, all this is
happened before at all. This is happening again. Right. It's
babble. They call it babble on. Right. They call Rome babble on.
St. Peter does St. John does. Right. So yeah, I, I, that's, that's
what I was alluding to and suggesting. I think fleshed out here
a little more. And very on topic because we were kind of
talking about that. Yeah, very much, very much. So does that, does
that clear things up for you.
Caleb? It does. You know, I have like a slight amendment. It may not be an answer to this one,
I base. So just, um, is that all right? Go for it. Go for it. Um, what do you think about like the,
the whole God's, um, confusing their language, that sort of thing? Is there some kind of particular
correlation you can think of there or? Well, that's the, so that's about the dividing of the nations.
So like when Junerotomy32 refers back to this...
Tower of Babel, they talk about when God divided the nations.
And one of the things that divides the nations is that they all have different languages.
Yeah.
That makes sense, I guess.
Yep.
All right.
Thank you very much for calling.
We're going to take another call.
We have Caesar calling from the frozen, frozen north up in Alberta.
So are we going to be pettings and say his name should really be pronounced Kaisar?
Kaisar?
I don't know.
How do you pronounce it, Caesar?
Welcome to the-
of Spears Podcast. Hello, Father. Thank you for taking my call. Yeah, she's
there. I mean, depending on the language, yeah, she's a requester in German or whatever.
Or Kaiser in Latin. Kaiser. Kaiser in Latin, yeah, yeah. But the Caesar or Cesar in French,
It's all good. I know I know myself so I'll recognize you all in Chesare in
So it's on your mind.
Yeah, thank you for taking my call.
I just I mean, this subject is not an easy one.
So I'm pretty sure you don't have a straight answer for it, but.
I was like continually when I read the Bible, it's always this pattern of.
the victim played those are been colonized in this case the Jews they played the victim and then vice versa and
When I read history, it's always when someone gets colonized. They play the victim and
That victimization lasts for like hundreds and hundreds of years within the community
And it seems like they don't get over it until
They get their revenge and I'm like, okay, like I was reading Hosea today and
And yes, all this criticism over the halletry, but then I'm like,
It's the pattern will come anyways, like they're going to play the victim and it's going
to last for hundreds and hundreds of years until it's returned to the, like they can make
their revenge somehow.
And like I'm like, okay, but I don't know, like what do you think about, like it's this
constant pattern that's like this patient that God has over his people.
I'm not sure.
Like, I don't know.
Do you have anything to say about that?
I don't know.
I mean, the pattern that we see in the Old Testament is that, and God says this to Israel,
basically, things are going to be okay as long as you're faithful to me, as long as you obey
the Torah, right?
And it says this in the text, when they become disobedient to that, God brings judgment
And the point of the judgment is not to, you know, beat them over the head because he's mad.
It's to chasing them and bring them back to faithfulness, right?
And so certainly along the way you get limitations, the things have gone very badly and so forth.
But, you know, there are moments when Israel returns to faithfulness under leaders like Josiah that we just mentioned.
So
You know what we should bring from that is not, okay, you know, this is what I, this is
my opinion of the nation of Israel and the Old Testament, rather, right?
But, but rather that when bad things happen in our own lives, whether it's overwhelming
or, you know, the relatively minor things that happen to most of us, that our response to
that should be, okay, this is God chasing me so that I will come to repentance.
Right so
You know, it's important when we read the scriptures to look at them and ask the question,
how do I use this that I'm reading for my repentance? Not how do I use this that I'm reading for my
opinion about somebody else, but rather for my own repentance? You know, like even when so like,
you know, we see that pattern in the Old Testament, but even for instance, when the city of Constance
and Snopel fell to the Ottoman Turks in 1453.
The response that you see from church leaders at the time was
God has brought this upon us because of our sins
Right, so they took it as repentance
And there are you know laments and so forth that are written amazing stuff written in Byzantine chant to express this at the time
and
And so that's the proper response is to receive any kind of disaster or suffer.
or whatever it might be as being a frankly a gift from God for our repentance.
Now that doesn't mean that suffering is good in and of itself. It's not.
It's just that we tend not to repent unless we're experiencing suffering.
That's just who human beings are. So yeah, I mean that's what we should draw out of that.
If you want to just ask the question of okay, well, how do it?
do we think about what Israel is doing at these various points?
You know, when they return to faithfulness, that's good.
And when they don't, then it's an example for us of how not to be.
So yeah, Father, do you have anything you wanted to add to that?
We have specifically on the angle of sort of the revenge of the colonized.
This is why the canonical Bible, right?
is stands opposed to the traditions of
zealotry that evolved and we did an episode, the third episode we did on the history of Israel where we talked about the
Hasmonians, we talked a lot about this. So the Judea, the Judeans, are the victims of the colonial violence of the Greek
so you kids.
They respond with the Maccabee and Revolt and a lot of violence and revenge taking and establish an independent Judea
But part of them establishing an independent Judea such that the Greek Celucids don't reinvade is they make peace treaties including with Rome
And that tree with Rome ends up getting them colonized by Rome.
Right. And the oppression's starting all over again and becoming worse. And then by the time you get to the new testament, you have zealot groups that are opposing Rome, trying to take revenge, trying to liberate themselves through violence.
and two of the two of Christ's 12 disciples,
remembers of Zealot groups, one of them,
say Simon the Zealot is a saint,
the other one Judas is scary it, definitely not.
That's Paul Paul was a zealot that is a lot phase you got radicalized early on and then repents of it
Because what does that lead to well? What is it lead to in the first century?
It leads to the destruction of the temple the destruction of Judea the expulsion of the Jewish people
Right completely from Jerusalem and the surrounding area
So the perspective of the canonical scriptures is that
uh
responding to colonial violence with revenge taking
Just continues a cycle of violence and revenge taking
whereas
As Christ says when you don't repay evil with evil, but you overcome evil with good
Then it is transformative
right? That the the the hasmonia in a way
The zealot way is a way that just you live by the sword you die by the sword
It's just a way that creates more violence and destruction in the world
And so the counter examples right we've got first macabees
But you've also got second macabees about the macabrean martyrs
Right who stay true and faithful to God to their deaths
They're not willing
They're not willing to kill
They're willing to die.
The apostles were not willing to kill.
They were willing to die.
Christ himself was willing to die.
And so that is the way that the canonical scriptures describe our response to colonial
violence or any oppression, anything of that sort.
a willingness to die for what is true and good.
and beautiful, not a willingness to kill for it.
Yeah. Does that make sense, Zezer?
Follow up just one thing.
Sure.
So the other sub question to that is those who are willing to
go on the road of repentance instead of playing the victim for hundreds of years
from generation to generation and try to put like anger within the family
New York.
Those who are willing to repent and adapt and just get away with all that anger, all that.
They have no choice but to kind of adapt to the colonizer culture in a sense as an option B.
And that's also a problem by itself because then they have to kind of deal with other problems.
And then if they don't want to go A, neither B, they want to stay like in between,
They will be as like it's going to be like a self-isolation in a sense.
And yeah, it will lead to martyredum, which is extremely difficult to be in that position.
But yeah, that's my final thought on it.
Yeah, yeah, martyredum is a heroic path.
But yeah, that's what was required of the macabrean martyreds, right?
They would not literally eat pork, they would not.
They would not you to Greek Hellenic culture and so yeah, and I mean there's there's also
someone there's also it like it also kind of depends like to repent is to be faithful to what God has
commanded right and you can be faithful to what God has commanded in many different cultural
expressions so a good example I would say from history is that you know the the when the Middle
The least was...
almost completely Christian, right? There are many different cultures that were
represented there. You had Greek speaking culture, you had Syriac speaking
culture, Persian speaking culture, etc., etc. Eventually you get the Muslim
invasions that come in and take over the whole region. And then, you know, there
had been some Arabic present, but eventually Arabic becomes the language
almost everywhere.
And the Christians that are there adopt the Arabic language.
There's nothing sinful about that, not remotely.
You can be absolutely a faithful Christian and speak Arabic.
I know many, many.
And yet at the same time, they did not, I mean, some did apostasize,
but there are faithful Christians remained faithful to that.
So they did not take on all of the culture of those who had conquered them.
They you know took on the language and maybe some customs. I'm not an expert in
those things, but you can be faithful in the midst of that experience. And there are some
kinds of adaptations that are perfectly fine. And then there's some that are not perfectly
fine. Right. So one has to be discerning and not simply say, well, I have to be, it's
not just A or B, you know, one can be faithful within the midst of whatever is going on.
And if martyrdom is required, then martyrdom is required.
But it's also possible to be
you know, the leaven that leavens the whole lump, God willing.
Christianity changed the Roman Empire, pagan Empire, demon worshiping Empire,
and Christianity did that by being faithful even in the midst of persecution.
And Christians had many cultures, even in the early Roman Empire,
and yet remained faithful to Christ. So it is possible, although not easy for sure.
for sure. So thanks very much for calling. We're going to take one more call.
one last little note. Oh yeah, go ahead father.
Victimhood is an attitude when chooses to take upon themselves.
I know people who have faced legitimate persecution and hardship and difficulty and hatred,
etc., in their life, who do not view themselves or portray themselves or conduct themselves as if
if they were victims.
Yeah.
Yeah. All the other
hand a week or so ago, I saw a video in which a the pastor of a very large
church in North Carolina was talking about how conservative Christians are
marginalized and hated. And I'm like, bro, you're a you're a wealthy conservative
Christian man in North Carolina.
Okay, you are one of the least persecuted people on earth.
You have like all the cards, bro.
Like, you're fine.
Okay.
You are not a victim.
Okay, but you can, it doesn't matter.
You can take that upon yourself.
Yeah. Okay.
Like a conservative Christian pastor, Protestant pastor in North Carolina is sort of like a white woman
in a Starbucks inside a target.
Okay, like wow you are in your place, okay?
This is your last gonna cancel you father Steven
All right anyway, all right baby because I tell them the truth
Okay, all right, we're gonna take one more call
and we have Adrian calling from Illinois and Adrian wants to know father of
about what you referred to as the quote unquote
pre-incarnate Christ.
So Adrian, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Good afternoon, fathers.
I updated my question a little bit
because I actually went and opened the Bible and read it.
And I hope this is like a baronstein, baronstein,
bearers thing, but I'm not seeing Angel
anywhere in Exodus in the Orthodox study Bible.
So I don't know if this is some bad information.
I was given for several years and I just never went back and corrected it.
Or if there's something else I'm missing here, I'm sure you guys can obviously enlighten all this whole more.
Okay, lay it out, father. Exodus. What passage are you looking at it?
He's talking about the, the, are you talking about the killing of the firstborn? Is that what you're referring to Adrian or something?
talking about the killing of the Assyrian army.
Oh!
Well, I was way off.
They laid siege to Jerusalem.
Yes.
With Sinac rib.
Yeah.
Although Christ does, I mean, Christ does show up in the Exodus.
I mean, there is an angel there, right?
The angel in whom God places his name.
Yeah.
He's fighting against the Egyptians directly.
And then when they're at the where they're at the Red Sea,
yeah, the guy who was on before us was talking about this,
I think, with their ethyrids.
you're getting ready to cross the cloud and the angel go behind them like between the Israelites
and Ferris horses. So there is an angel there right who is we identified with the pre-carnit
Christ but that's not what I was talking about earlier. I was talking about earlier was the
the Assyrian siege of Jerusalem. Is that clear things that I mean? I jumped to the the more common
and Sunday school story then, as opposed to what we're actually doing.
talking about it's okay to it's okay to admit that you mean you know the movie
the 10 Commandments with Charles and Heston yeah they haven't done a good movie
about the Assyrian siege of Jerusalem to be fair that would be like that would be like
NC 17 plus plus plus plus maybe the well the question is what you do with the rats
That's true because there's there was so
What it says in the text is that the angel Lord came there at night this year camp and wipes everybody out, right?
Josephus, when he's talking about that episode in antiquities, says that rats came up from the city like the sewer and like,
like, and eat all the bow strings of the Assyrian troops so they couldn't make war.
And so the interesting hypothesis that a lot of biblical scholars have is that what happened is because we also read that when they're laying siege to Jerusalem, they stopped up all the they stopped up the water supply.
And so they stopped up the water supply.
Rats right came up out of the the drainage system and there was a plague outbreak.
And so the way that God killed the Assyrians in the camp was through the plague, like the
bubonic plague, or something similar.
So that's what you do with the rats in the movie.
Yeah.
So do you just go for the CGI Angel of the Lord, taking everybody out, or do you rat thousands?
Yes.
Anyway.
All right. Well, thanks for calling Adrian.
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, let's continue on our journey.
I am sated by our interactions with the
community. All right.
All right.
Yeah. Thanks for calling everybody.
Back to Nebuchadnezzar in the Bible.
I've got rid of all of the white women who are listening,
and all of the Protestant pastors in North Carolina.
Um.
So next place, Nebuchadnezzar comes up, of course, is in Second Kings or Fourth Kingdoms.
Chapter 24 and 25, and that, of course, is the story of Nebuchadnezzar coming up and
coming in and wrecking Chuta and destroying the temple and capturing Jerusalem and starting
to deport people into exile.
There it's portrayed pretty clearly as
Nebuchadnezzar is coming as sort of
the agent of God's judgment against Judah for their faithlessness, setting them into exile.
But also, it's important in second kings that second kings portrays it as, hey, you guys
brought this on yourselves.
Sort of in the way I was talking about to the caller about the Hasmodians making that deal
with Rome that backfired on them real good.
In second Kings 20 versus 12 through night.
It talks about how King Hezekiah, super genius, invited the Babylonian delegation to come
and see all the cool treasures he had in the temple.
I know.
Check out my sweet treasures.
Yes.
After which Isaiah points out that he's an idiot and tells him you realize as a result of
this.
The Babylonians are gonna come back and take all of this, right?
Like you see that coming, right?
And are you ready for how that passage ends?
As a guy is happy.
Because Isaiah tells him that the Babylonians are gonna come back and do this after he's dead.
So he's just happy. Well, there'll be peace in my lifetime.
Yeah, sorry kids.
So, Hezekiah, not the sharpest tool in the shed, right, as second Kiggs 20 presents him at least.
He's wicked and repentant, but through it all, not the best leader, right, from just a practical perspective.
So, the McKinnons are also, of course, has a prominent role, I'll be it in the back.
background as a looming threat in the book of Jeremiah. And that is because he is looming
as a threat. He is preparing to invade Judah and and Lacey to Jerusalem. And Jeremiah, being
the true prophet of God, is informed by God that David can as there's going to win. That
he is going to conquer. He is going to destroy the city. And he's going to do that because
of the wicked.
of Israel. Chapter 21 for example, right? Jeremiah is informed of that and
pronounces that Jeremiah 25 verse 9 is another place where
David Kineszers mentioned where Jeremiah makes clear that this is again God's
judgment coming upon the people of Judah and that David Kineszers the
instrument of that judgment. It gets even more explicit in Jeremiah 27,
verses one through eight where
Yahweh the God of Israel literally calls debit kites or his servant again a demon worshiping God king
Stop to boy that out again. Yes
So this is what it's starting with verse one in the beginning of the reign of Zedakaya the son of Josiah king of Judah
This word came to Jeremiah from the Lord thus the Lord said to me
Make yourself straps and yoke bars and put them on your neck, send words to the king of
either
the king of Moab, the king of the sons of Ammon, the king of Tyre, and the king of Scydon
by the hand of the endvoys who have come to Jerusalem to Zedekaya, King of Judah, give
them this charge for their masters.
Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel.
This is what you shall say to your masters.
It is I who by my great power and my art-stretched arm have made the earth with the men and
animals that are on the earth, and I give it to whomever it seems right to me.
Now I have given all these lands into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, my
servant.
And I have given him also the beast of the field to serve him.
All the nations shall serve him and his son and his grandson
until the time of his own land comes, and many nations and great kings shall
make him their slave. But if any nation or kingdom will not
serve this nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon and put its neck
under the yoke of the king of Babylon, I will punish that nation with the
sword, with famine and with pestilence, declares the Lord
until I have consumed it by his hand."
And man that's...
I'm probably hard to swallow for a lot of people to say the least, right?
So not only is he is he speaking to Zedekaya, the king of Judah, but he invites emissaries
from Eidom, Moab, from all the neighboring Ammon, right, Tyred, Sidon, the Phoenicians,
right, all the neighboring countries to see this too. God hasn't put a yolk on.
Yes, right.
to say it to be physically Jeremiah puts on a yolk.
And comes and delivers this message like wearing this yoke, right?
That either you can say that that navigate God has decided to give Nebuchadnezzar for a certain period of time.
Yes, right. All of these lands. And so he's going to have them so you guys can either surrender them to Nebuchadnezzar and we can do this the easy way.
Or you can try and resist
evaconizer which will be
resisted God and therefore you will
get wrecked, right? Right? Soared famine, pestilence, right? It's it's it's all
going to go very badly, okay? So as you mentioned, this was received somewhat
poorly, right? By the people and part of what's going on here in this whole
section of Jeremiah is Jeremiah is of course telling the truth, right? It is a true
profit of God, but there are these other people, these false prophets who claimed
prophets of Yahweh who are saying the exact opposite. Yes. Okay. And saying what people want to hear.
So of course the king and everybody else are believing those people who are telling them what they
want to hear, not Jeremiah. He's telling you what they don't want to hear and they're labeling Jeremiah as
a traitor, right? Why are you saying they're going to win and they're going to beat us? You're on
their side right you're a Babylonian shill right
Uh, you're paid off by, by Naboo Soros, uh, to spread this propaganda. Uh, right. So, um,
so they're, they're, they're pitting all this on him. And so in, in chapter 28, right, the next
chapter, uh, Han and I, one of these bogus prophets, uh, takes the yogurt breaks it. Right. Right.
Ha ha! It's- Yes, it says-
Hus says Yahweh, the God of Israel.
So he's got some Hutspa this hand.
Oh.
In two years, I will break the Yoke of Nebuchadnezzar.
And you know, you will be victorious
and everything will be fine, right?
And so then, you know, verses one through 14,
this unfolds sort of the end of that,
verse 12, 13, 14.
Jeremiah says, oh, no, no, no, no.
The Yoke of Nebuchadnezzar is a Yoke of iron.
It don't snap so...
We see now, right?
Like you're done, right?
And so the rest of Jeremiah thinks
that goes to Wilford Jeremiah,
they end up throwing him down a well
and then he gets taken to Egypt against his well,
Shades of Joseph.
But yeah, so Nebuchadnezzar there
is the sort of looming threat.
So, Zichil.
is prophesying within the context of exile.
So, Jerusalem is already done.
He's in one of the early deportations, to Babylon.
But he issues prophecies in chapter 26 against Tyre
and in chapters 29 and 30 of Ezekiel against Egypt
in which God is sort of threatening both Egypt and Tyre
with
Nebuchadnezzar. Right. That Nebuchadnezzar is sort of presented as this weapon that God has in
his arsenal to use to execute judgment against these wicked nations and kings. But of course,
if we're talking about Nebuchadnezzar, the place where Nebuchadnezzar is the most prominent in
the Bible, the place where he shows up in person and people interact with him and he interacts with
them is primarily the book of Daniel.
Yeah, yeah, because Daniel has a personal relationship with Nebuchadnezzar
Because in exile he's become a young official of the Babylonian court
And so that sort of starts in in Daniel chapter two
Daniel chapter two is where Nebuchadnezzar has had a dream and
He wants it interpreted but
Nebuchadnezzar is no dummy
me. So he.
He goes to all of his diviners and astrologers and all priests and the other usual suspects
and babble on and they say, oh yeah, we can interpret your dream for us.
Tell us about your dream and he's like, no, why don't you tell me what my dream was and
then tell me what it means.
Yeah.
So he's no dummy, right?
like if you guys can really tell all this stuff that you should know right like whatever
for saw, you should already know about from the stars or from entrails or whatever it is you're reading.
You should already know about it, right? Anybody can come up with some interpretation if I tell
it to them, right? Makes up that up, right? And of course, so none of them can without hearing it.
But Daniel is given a prophetic vision by God, and so he comes and not only tells
and then he could as or what his dream was.
he then interprets it. And this is the dream, of course, where Nebuchadnezzar saw the statue,
like the idol of a king, of an emperor, and the pieces of it as you descend from head to foot,
Arbate of different substances, so it goes from gold to silver to bronze to iron to the feet being
iron mixed with.
clay. Right. And Daniel interprets this as a succession of world empires with the neo-Bavillonian being the gold, then you get the Persians, then the Greeks, then Rome, and then finally a weakened Rome.
And then a stone is carved out not by human hands.
that stone is thrown in smashes, all of those empires, smashes the statue at the point of the iron mixed with clay,
and the stone then grows and becomes a mountain that fills the earth, like the mountain of God.
So this stone not made with human hands that becomes the mountain of God, the kingdom of God, the rule of God, through all the earth is the Messiah.
Right, so this is a messianic prophecy that's telling us that
guess what he's going to come in the Roman Empire.
And this is how Jewish folks read it at the time.
This is one of the reasons there was so much Messianic
fervor in the first century AD is they were understanding a bunch
of the prophecies in Daniel to be pointing to that time period
is the time when the Messiah would come.
And Christians, of course, held on to that interpretation of
those prophecies. Other on Christian Jews.
held onto other interpretations of those prophecies, but this is certainly one of them.
So, this is a place where, again, by virtue of doing this, Nebuchadnezzar is impressed
with Daniel's wisdom, spiritual insight, etc.
And so, he finds Nebuchadnezzar's favor, he advances in his court, he gets him leeway.
leeway as to his three friends.
of various names.
Shadrach, we should have been to go if you want their Babylonian names.
Azariah, Missael, and what's the third one?
And Anias, Azariah, Missael.
And so those three friends that become important in chapter three,
which again involves Devacadezza, the famous story that we were
read on Holy Saturday of the Tree Eudes, where a giant idol is constructed of
Debenchidesar. Because remember, the king is not only the king and the high priest
he's also divine himself and so is an object of worship. He receives worship,
Due to his divinity and being seen as
sort of in this case an embodiment of Naboo the son of
Marduk. And so the command is given that you know we're gonna set it up and at
a certain time when a group of musical instruments are played it's very
repetitious as you know if you've heard it read on Holy Saturday listing the
the answer.
over and over again. What all those instruments play with the signal plays that the signal is given everyone's going to bow and pray and offer worship and glorification to the image of
of Nebuchadnezzar, and of course Daniels III friends will not do this and so when they refuse to do this
multiple times they are thrown into a super heated furnace.
He did so high that the people who throw them in die from the heat, collateral damage,
but they of course are preserved and are joined in the furnace by a fourth man.
Here's our pre-incarnate Lord Jesus Christ again, who is with them in the flames
and the flames are to them. Is a dewey breeze as one of our hymns say. I do have to say
I miss the old translation.
of this story that we used to use in the
any of the archdiocese. Yeah, I think it was in
haphazard. On holy Saturday for one main reason,
that was the translation of the list of instruments.
Oh, and included sack butts included the sack butt.
That's right. And if you have never been around 10
year old ultra boys at the end of a holy week when they're all tired.
for them.
For these people the word sack but is the most hysterical thing. It's pretty great. There's
everybody said it gets said like five times and the trygon during the reading and those the kids
are falling out. They're I mean sack, sack butts are basically trombones. Yeah, but so which is a
pretty funny instrument for a 10 year old boy. Especially not out a lot of sleep. Sack but it's
It's just the great work.
Never composed by you man.
Right, and so Nebuchadnezzar here though, you get this element of him being this pagan king who is himself an object of worship who considers himself divine
And you get his sort of reticence because these are people who have found favor with him in the past, but
The duties of kingship you can't just cut someone slack, right?
It's not a thing you could do.
Remember what happened when the
the Assyrian Emperor started to show any kind of weakness whatsoever.
I mean, Marduk, you know, chills out once in a while.
I mean, come on.
Yeah.
Once in a while.
Very, very mostly savagery.
Savage.
Yeah, savage sort of Marduk.
So and then the passage that we won't spend a ton of time on this one.
are going to read through it and comment a little, but the other big one, and this is
major for Nebuchadnezzar because he is the protagonist really of this chapter, is chapter
four, which is the story of his temporary madness. The reason we're going to spend a ton
of time on it now is I think it's our second Halloween episode.
Yeah, the second or third maybe. We spend a lot of time on this passage talking about
So we're gonna go
back to it. We're going to touch on some things here. But if you want to like deeper dive
on his madness, the idea of madness in general, how that connects to figures like Enke
Dew in the epic of Gilgamesh as sort of a madman or a wild man, you can go and read all
or hear all that there or read it in the transcript. I think there's a transcript, but you
could also hear our dulcet tones as we describe it to you. It's a right 57 times.
That's...
Well, for now.
We'll move kind of quickly in chapter four, starting around verse four.
We've dropped some verses out here too.
So we're going to be kind of just moving through it, noting some pertinent things.
Yep. Okay.
I, Nebuchadnezzar was at ease in my house and prospering in my palace.
I saw a dream that made me afraid as I lay in bed, the fancies and the visions of my
head alarmed me. At last, Daniel came in before me, he who was named built to
Shazar, Bale to Shazar.
After the name...
of my God, and in whom is the spirit of the Holy Gods?" And I told him the dream, saying,
oh, Beltasazar, chief of the magicians, because I know that the spirit of the Holy Gods is in you
and that no mystery is too difficult for you. Tell me the visions of my dream that I saw and their
interpretation. The visions of my head as I lay in bed were these. I saw and behold a tree in the
midst of the earth and its height was great. The tree grew and became strong and its top reached
to heaven and it was visible to the
end of the whole earth. Its leaves are beautiful and it's fruit abundant and in it was food
for all. The beasts of the field found shade under it and the birds of the heavens lived
in its branches and all flesh was fed from it. So I saw it.
So Daniel like Shadrach Bishagad Bendigo is given because these functions, according
to the word, is given a Babylonian name, which as Father Andrew mentioned, is a theophoric
Babylonian name that is bell in it right mail
And in the text,
Debra Kinesa says,
built a Shazar after the name of my God, right.
And so this is written in the first person,
as you may have noticed.
Like this is the story about Debra Kinesa
is being told by Debra Kinesa as it's presented
in Daniel chapter four.
And so we're getting these things from his perspective.
So he sees Daniel as the chief of the magicians.
of all those advisors of all those magi right all those wise advisors he's the the most
prominent of them why because he was able to interpret that other dream and even tell him what
it was yeah right and so he knows that he has divine spirits within him who are in touch with him
right so we're getting this filtered right through Navi Kineszor's sort of pagan worldview right but
part of what we're gonna see unfold is about
How maybe that worldview gets changed and
Right shifted and so he starts this time he doesn't make Daniel tell the dream he starts telling about the dream
At about this tree. Okay now we're certain. All right. I saw in the visions of my head as I lay in bed.
Visions of sugar plums dancing. Sorry. And the old watcher.
Sure, a holy one came down from heaven.
A lot of people get excited when we mention the watchers.
Well, yeah, this is this is the passage in the canonical scriptures, right?
So, of course, the watchers are in the book of Enic, but that mentions watchers as a class of angels.
Yeah. Yeah.
Good. Yeah.
He proclaimed aloud and said thus,
chop down the tree and lock off its branches, strip off its leaves and scatter its fruit,
but the beasts flee from under it and the birds from its branches,
but leave the stump of its roots in the earth bound with a band of iron and bronze
Amid the tender grass, the field, let him be wet.
the dew of heaven. Let us portion be with the beasts in the grass of the earth. Let us mind be
changed from a man's and let a beast's mind be given to him. And let seven periods of time pass over him.
The sentence is by the decree of the watchers, the decision by the word of the holy ones,
to the end that the living may know that the most high rules the kingdom of men and gives it to whom he
will and sets over at the loliest of men.
Okay. So, notice here...
This is described as the decree of the watchers
Right, so this is gods and jealous counsel
Right, this is presented as
They have ruled like as as a group
They have ruled on this
That they're going to issue this judgment upon the tree which spoilers right is Nebuchadnezzar himself
Right and the deal Babylonian Empire that he personifies right that he sums up in his
person, right, that these things are going to happen to him. And why the purpose is that
the living, so not just devicate as there, not just these relights, the living, all people,
right, would know that it is the most high God, most high is the title that angelic beings used to
refer to Yahweh, the God of Israel, that he's the one who rules the kingdom of men and gives
whom he will, meaning Nebuchadnezzar has power and authority over the world because Yahweh,
the God of Israel has given it to him. Not Marduk, not he seized it for himself through his
own trudess, etc. Think about what Christ says to Pontius Pilate. You would have no authority over
of me if it had been not been given to you from above. Right.
All right. Continuing on, verse 19.
When Daniel, whose name was Belta Shazar, was dismayed for a while, and his thoughts alarmed
him.
The king answered and said, Belta Shazar, let not the dream or the interpretation alarm
you."
Belta Shazar answered and said, My Lord, may the dream be for those who hate you and
its interpretation for your enemies.
The tree you saw, which grew and became strong, so that its top reached to heaven, and
it was visible to the end of the whole earth, whose leaves were beautiful in its fruit
abundant, and in which was food for all, under which beasts of the field found shade, and
He knew his branches, the Bur-
the heavens lived, it is you who are the king who have grown and become strong. Your greatness
has grown and reaches to heaven and your dominion to the ends of the earth. And because the king saw
a watcher, a holy one, coming down from heaven, this is the interpretation of king. It is the
decree of the most high which has come upon my Lord the king that you should be driven from among men
and your dwelling should be with the beasts of the field. You should be made to eat grass like an
and you should be wet with
the dew of heaven, and seven periods of time shall pass over to you, till you know that
the most high rules the kingdom of men and gives it to whom he will.
And as it was commanded to leave the stump of the roots of the tree, your kingdom shall
be confirmed for you from that time that you know that heaven rules.
Therefore, O King, let my counsel be acceptable to you.
Break off your sins by practicing righteousness and your niceties by showing mercy to the oppressed
that there may perhaps be a link.
your prosperity. Oh, so had, yeah, so notice that this same judgment is referred to as the judgment of the
watchers, the judgment of the most high, right, of God himself, and heaven, right? Notice also the
subtle shift, so that the angel in his dream said, what?
dream said, so that the living may know, Daniel says that this madness is going to come
upon you will last until you know you never can nether know. Right, that it's the most
high who rules the kingdom of men and gives it to whom he will. Okay. So this language
of the decree of the watchers of the council being the decree of God himself being the
decree of heaven, sort of the whole government, right?
This is all kingly language that God is using.
God is here trying, speaking to Nebuchadnezzar in language that a king would understand, right?
But the idea here is, y'all, they got to be Israel is the Great King.
Right? And you, Nebuchadnezzar, are a vassal.
To whom the Great King, the most high, has given
a certain dominion for a certain time. Right? And perhaps you ought not think more highly of yourself than that.
And so then notice Daniel adds at the end of what Father Andrew just read. Right.
when he's giving him counsel, he's giving him advice, he says, break off your sins by practicing righteousness.
And you're iniquities by showing mercy.
to be oppressed. He doesn't just say, hey, here's a list of sins you're committing
stop. He says, here are the things that you need to do as opposed to what you've been
doing. And when you do those things, when you become a good king, then you as a good
King will be a true vassal.
Because a true vassal of the great king represents the great king perfectly in his rule.
Right? You're like a vicar, right? On earth. And so you need to represent, you need to be an image
of the rule of the most high of the great king. Right? And then this judgment would not be necessary.
So go ahead, good deed.
First of all, this came upon King Nebuchadnezzar.
immediately the word was fulfilled against Nebuchadnezzar. He was driven from among men in eight
grass like an ox, and his body was wet with the dew of heaven until his hair grew as long as
eagles feathers, and his nails were like birds claws. At the end, at the end, like full-houred hues.
At the end of the days, I, Nebuchadnezzar, lifted my eyes to heaven, and my reason returned to me,
and I blessed the most high and praised and honored him who lives forever.
For his
Dominion is an everlasting dominion and his kingdom endures from generation to generation.
All the inhabitants of the earth are counted as nothing, and he does, according to his
will, among the host of heaven and among the inhabitants of the earth, and none can stay
his hand or say to him, what have you done?
At the same time my reason returned to me, and for the glory of my kingdom my majesty
and splendour returned to me.
My counselors and my lords sought me and I was established in my kingdom, and still more
greatness was added to me.
Now I need a kidnether.
praise and extol and honor the king of heaven for all his works are right and his ways are just
and those who walk and pride he is able to humble.
Notice that line he does according to his will among the hosts of heaven and among the inhabitants of
the earth, right? So he's not only a god to the humans, right, the little humans on earth,
but he is a God to the God's
God's who never-
is been worshipping. Right? They are to him as humans are to them. Right? And what we have here ultimately is a confession of repentance and faith from
from Nebuchadnezzar, which is never in Scripture taken back.
Because we don't we don't really see him again after this.
Scripture. Yes. So there's not any
in the canonical scriptures that he turned his back on this somehow and forgot his lesson
or became a pagan again. Yeah, might we see him in the kingdom of heaven? Who knows? Who knows?
And keep in mind, what's required of someone who's not a king of Israel?
Right, you didn't have to go get circumcised to keep kosher, right? That's not expected of him.
Right.
This is the kind of thing that's expected of him to be a righteous gentile. Yeah.
I think you know, and we've covered a pretty huge swath of history here and some, you know, world sweeping stuff.
I think that as
as we look at the life of Nebuchadnezzar and then all the ways that he
is used in the Bible.
He's a symbol of God's judgment.
He's the tool of God's judgment.
He himself is judged by God.
And a lot of the themes here, of course,
are about rulership and sovereignty and conquest
and all the seven power and might.
I think one of the things that I take away from a lot of this
is that a big piece of the Christian life is about truly
knowing that God is the Lord, that He is the Lord of all.
And so many sins, I think we commit because we don't know that deep down.
Like sins that we commit in private, that we think no one's going to see.
I mean, there's a lot of warnings in the Bible about people who think that.
God is Lord of all. He sees everything you do. He knows every thought that you have.
He knows every time a thought that's suggested to you by a demon that you welcome it in,
that you entertain it. He sees all the things that you do.
And if you had a sense of his presence with you, probably a lot less likely to send.
That's certainly true for me.
But then...
And also, it's not just the sins that you commit because you think no one's watching,
but it's also the failures to trust in the love of God.
Right?
God is love.
It says this in the Scripture.
Everything that we see Him doing and the stuff that we just talked about is His provision
for the repentance, the salvation of every person involved.
And a lot of the sins that we see Israel commit are about not trusting God.
We're going to take care of this ourselves.
Whatever it might be, whether it's victory and war, whether it's hunger and thirst, whatever
it might be.
Things go badly when you don't trust in God, which includes obeying the things that
he said, like we saw how it kind of ended badly for even St. Josiah, a good, good king.
even he decided to go out to battle when that was not what God told him to do.
And in our own lives individually, but then also in the lives of our communities,
it is trust in God that should drive much of what we do.
I, not that long ago, I actually had a conversation with a bishop.
And he was asking me in my opinion, I was...
kind of surprise. He was asking me on my opinion about a number of practical matters in the church.
And there's one point where I said, you know, probably wanting to sound wise,
well, it's difficult to get money for this or that. And he said, if we need money for something,
we'll just ask God for it and He'll give it. Which really struck me because this is not,
you know, this is a bishop with many years of experience, many, many years of experience.
That doesn't sound to the world like a practical thing to say.
But this is actually how God operates.
If something is what God wants and we trust in Him and we are faithful to Him, He'll give what it is that's needed.
It may not be what we think is needed, but it is what is needed.
And all of this comes within an acknowledgement, not just acknowledgement like, okay, I agree that that's true,
deep knowledge.
that God is the Lord, that God is the Lord.
And this is different from the way that pagan saw their gods as lords.
Like Marduk, as we saw, is this violent maniac most of the time.
And so acknowledging him as Lord is about, like, please don't hurry.
And a lot of religion, frankly, goes that way.
Some of it even going by the name of Christian.
But that's not the God of the...
scriptures that's not the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob, the Father, the Son, the Holy Spirit.
That's not our God. Our God loves us and is always, always, always acting in love for us.
And so his lordship, his sovereignty in our lives is always so that we might be saved.
It would have been perfectly logical for his judgment of Nebuchadnezzar to be...
to crush him to destroy his kingdom and that would be it. But instead what you get is, I mean,
it's tough. What he goes through is tough, very difficult living essentially like a beast in
madness for a long time, but it's for his repentance. It's for his salvation. God didn't, it doesn't
want to just, you know, it's not about punishing like you did a bad thing that became a spiritual
You know, you got what you deserve.
Rather, it's about bringing...
him to the point where we left him where he's acknowledging the sovereignty of God and
acknowledging that he is the true king of everything and that Nebuchadnezzar is not the
king of the universe. Notice the last thing he says, now I, Nebuchadnezzar, praise and
extol and honor the king of heaven. In other words, it's not me, Nebuchadnezzar, I'm not
the king of heaven, I'm not the king of the universe. The king of heaven.
He's the one who does everything that he wills among the hosts of heavens, among the inhabitants of the earth and
No one can call him to account
There are many ways I think to motivate oneself in the Christian life many ways to be motivated towards faithfulness
This is one
This is one of them to to know that God is the Lord that he is rule over all that he is almighty as
as we say in the Creed,
and that he loves us
and he's exercising that lordship for us.
For us.
You know, in this judgment of Nebuchadnezzar,
he describes this great tree that shelters and provides food
and all this kind of stuff.
And that's not bad.
That's what a king should be.
Right, and so if Nebuchadnezzar is
that properly because he's returned to that position, then he is that because he's imaging
who God is, God vking overall, the one who provides everything, the one who is himself
the tree of life. Right? So that's why the road to that, because it might...
be difficult to really know deep down that God is King of all and Lord of all.
But the road to that I think, I think the surest road is the road of gratitude.
Now, the good thing is the Scripture never says in everything, feel thankful, but rather
in everything give thanks, which is an action you can take no matter what your emotional
status. You don't have to feel that God is Lord. You don't have to...
be yield-thankful. You might, and it's nice, you know, if you do, but to give thanks, to
acknowledge, to confess with our lips that God is Lord and to give thanks to him in the
ways that are proper, both with our words and our worship and our actions. Because if
you know that God is Lord and that he, everything belongs to him, then that means you also
be generous. And you can be generous no matter how you feel because it's an action that you take.
So we exercise that gratitude, we exercise that generosity. These are really in some ways they're
kind of the same one thing. And in so doing, then we come to know that he is our king and that he does
truly love love us and exercises his kingship for us. So that's what I have to say about
God never kidnés her today.
There are many ways to motivate yourself in 50 ways to leave your lover.
50 ways to name your marduk.
That's what we call in the biz, a callback.
Nice.
So, if you believe certain reformed baptists with YouTube channels, we orthodox are a mean
lot because we think everyone who's not an orthodox Christian is going to.
and probably a lot of Orthodox Christians too, as we're just Ron teaching that works
righteousness. And such folk will not listen to our protestations otherwise either. But
I think what we see in Nebuchadnezzar is one of the basic biblical building blocks of
the actual teaching and tradition of the church.
on this subject. Which is that? Not only is it possible that God is working in the lives of people outside of the church and by the church, I mean the Orthodox Church.
It's got to be honest and above board here. Not only is it possible, not only is it likely?
Not only is it just true that he is working in the lives of people outside the earth at
X-Search.
He is working in the lives and hearts and souls of every human being.
Every human being has a relationship that could probably be described as personal in some sense with God and with Christ.
There is no one who doesn't.
It may not be a good, positive relationship, but it's a relationship.
Right.
They may be resisting what he's trying to do.
in their life, maybe resisting his voice,
maybe resisting his calls to repentance, to faithfulness.
Maybe suppressing the knowledge of him,
from their minds, to their hearts, to their souls.
But he's still there.
He's still there.
They live in his creation. They live in his world.
To me, I think that's a through line
through everything we talked about tonight.
Whether it's these events.
the sort of world events of a bygone world that are very similar to events that
play out over and over again in our world, whether it's Nebuchadnezzar himself by
his own first-person testimony, whether it's him as a figure looming on the
world stage, God is involved in all of this. God is active in all of this.
Scriptures are just revealed.
the ways in which he's active and acting in and through these events. How it is
that he is related to them, how it is that he is related to Nebuchadnezzar. And in
that final section we read, Nebuchadnezzar coming to be aware of his relationship
with the God who created him and everything else. This is true for everyone. There
There's no one of whom it is not true.
even a giant, even the most despicable person you'll ever meet.
Right. God still desires that that person should not perish, but turn and live.
God is still calling that person to repentance and faith.
As I've pointed out in Bible studies, even when Christ is calling
Herod or the Pharisees because Herod literal slurs.
the original Greek, calling the heresies, snakes, whitewash tombs, vibrant everything under
the sun, even when he's doing that Christ is still talking to them.
He's still trying to get their attention. He's still trying to get them to listen, trying
to get them to repent. If he didn't care, if he didn't have a relationship with them,
he wouldn't be talking to them, he just let them perish.
And their hypocrisy.
in their sins and their wickedness. But he doesn't. He still talks to them. And he uses
whatever kind of rhetoric he needs to try to get through to them.
And why this is important to know it's not just to affirm, important to affirm, so that,
oh, those people online will know that no actually us orthodox people are nice people after all.
I
The reason it's important for us to know is that this gives us an important window to an aspect of what love is.
What it means to love another person.
Especially people who we might not find innately lovable in terms of how they as a person in their present state
And I as a person in my present state do or do not interface well.
Do or do not get a
long while. What it means ultimately, from one perspective at least, to love a person,
is to find the ways in which God is working in their life, the ways in which God is speaking
to them, the things that God is calling them to, and join in that call, support that movement
of God in their life.
Encourage it.
future it.
do everything we can to facilitate that person following the calling of God in their life.
We see again and again in the scripture whether it's Nebuchadnezzar, the emperor of
the world, or Cornelius, this ensurian and Acts, or name in the leper, right?
even though these people have very limited knowledge of who the true God is.
and what he wants from them.
When they gain a little, they're faithful to it.
And God gives them more.
In the case of Nebuchadnezzar,
he sends Daniel to facilitate that.
Name in the leper, it's the prophet, Cornelius, it's Saint Peter.
For a whole bunch of people you've met will need
know it's you. You're the one who's there in that person's life to give them
the more. To help continue the process. And it's in the process of you
participating in that. God doesn't need you for it, but you participating in that.
You being the one who God works through.
To continue to reach that person and transform them is how you're going to find and work
out your salvation.
That's part of how he's going to speak to you and part of how you're going to answer
the call that he's giving to you, how you're going to experience the change that he's bringing
to your life.
So, Kinesa was this big important person.
But Daniel is maybe more important because he was important to Nebuchadnezzar.
You don't have to be a big important person.
You can be some kid in exile.
You can be some Galilee in Fisherman.
There's probably a literate.
You can just be you.
But you can be a part of the most important things that are happening in the world right now,
which aren't the things everybody's talking about on social media isn't the things that's
going out of the news channel.
It's what God is doing in the lives of people.
So that's my commentary.
May man, a good ol' nebuchadnezzar.
Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight. Thank you very much for listening, everybody.
If you didn't happen to talk to us tonight live, we'd like to hear from you. You can email us
at Lordofspirits.anationfaith.com. You can message us at our Facebook page, or you can
leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lordofspirits. And if you have basic questions about
Orthodox Christianity, you need help to find a parish. Go to Orthodoxintro.org.
Join us for our live broadcast on the second 4th Thursdays.
the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. Roodle me this my brother can you handle it.
Your style to my style you can't hold a candle to it.
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page you can join our discussion group. Leave
those ratings and those reviews but share this show with a friend, family member or an
enemy who might love it, hate it or I don't know be indifferent to it.
And probably be sure to go to www.inxfordfaith.com.suporote and help make sure we and lots of
whether AFR podcasters stay on the air.
from the rich and I'm out robbing banks, given to the poor, and I always give thanks.
Thank you, good night. God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio. And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
the beasts and the elders and the number of them was ten
10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.